<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moderation: or Arguments and motives tending thereunto, humbly tendred to the Honourable Members of Parliament. As also indifferently calculated for common consideration. Together with a brief touch of the reputed German Anabaptists, and Munster tragedy. By S.T.</title>
            <author>S. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T54</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1015_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867153</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867153</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119445</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95594)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119445)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 150:E1015[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moderation: or Arguments and motives tending thereunto, humbly tendred to the Honourable Members of Parliament. As also indifferently calculated for common consideration. Together with a brief touch of the reputed German Anabaptists, and Munster tragedy. By S.T.</title>
                  <author>S. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, dwelling in Aldersgate-street, next door to the sign of the Peacock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 3. 1659"; the imprint year has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Moderation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119445:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:119445:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>MODERATION: OR ARGUMENTS and MOTIVES tending thereunto, Humbly tendred to the Honourable MEMBERS of PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo indifferently calculated for common conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with a brief Touch of the reputed German Anabaptiſts, AND Munſter Tragedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> S. T.</p>
            <q>Let your moderation be known unto all men, the Lord is at hand. <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 4. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Shouldeſt thou not alſo have had compaſſion on thy fellow-ſervant, even as I had pity on thee? <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18 33.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Who is a wiſe man and endued with knowledge amongſt you. Let him ſhew out a good converſation his works with meekneſs of wiſdom. But the wiſdom that is from above, is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without <hi>partiality,</hi> without hypocriſie. <bibl>
                  <hi>James</hi> 3. 13, 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>In revenge of injuries, he is the loſer that gers the better. <bibl>
                  <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Henry <hi>the fourth of</hi> France <hi>was wont to ſay,</hi>That he made all the days of ſuch <hi>Golden,</hi> who had moſt offended him, that ſo the <hi>Lead</hi> of their <hi>Fault</hi> might be darkened by the <hi>Gold</hi> of his <hi>Goodneſs.</hi>
               <hi>Vid.</hi> Traps <hi>Comment.</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 21. Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> Henry Hills, <hi>dwelling in</hi> Alderſgate-ſtreet, <hi>next door to the Sign of the</hi> Peacock. 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119445:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119445:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the diviſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> there were <hi>great</hi> thoughts of heart: but though the breaches of <hi>England</hi> (in Church and State) are <hi>very many, and, indeed great,</hi> yet how few do ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, with a right ſpirit, lay them to heart, <hi>mourn</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, <hi>ſearch</hi> the cauſes indifferently on all hands, <hi>ſtudy</hi> the Remedies, <hi>apply</hi> Balm and Oyl, and <hi>cry mightily</hi> unto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for <hi>help</hi> and <hi>healing,</hi> without whom, in vain is the help of man? But in ſtead hereof men are ſupine, ſenſleſs, touching common danger and Chriſtian duty; or otherwiſe, ſome with <hi>virulency,</hi> others with <hi>vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> rejoycing in uncovering their neighbours nakedneſs, triumphing and ſporting themſelves over others <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>ſorrows,</hi> thereby <hi>widening</hi> our breaches, <hi>adding</hi> fewel to the fire, <hi>augmenting</hi> the ſin and ſhame of our Nation, and <hi>rendring</hi> its miſerable wounds <hi>more</hi> incurable. All which, as by <hi>words,</hi> ſo by vicious and luxuriant <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> iſſuing from <hi>violent paſſions, humour, faction,</hi> others from <hi>filthy frothineſs</hi> with which the City and Nation is <hi>peſtered</hi> at this day, as with a contagious corrupted air: which ſheweth, that through our <hi>long inteſtine</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and animoſities (eſpecially thoſe among the <hi>Godly</hi> of <hi>all</hi> perſwaſions, for which I deſire <hi>more</hi> to mourn) <hi>Religion</hi> wants cheriſhing, which ſubdues the exorbitant luſts of men, <hi>Irreligion</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm</hi> begins to overgrow us, and the <hi>fear of God,</hi> and the power of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> is brought to a very low ebb in the world, to the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of God and his Goſpel, the <hi>dammage</hi> of all ſorts, and the great <hi>detriment</hi> and <hi>hazard</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Proteſtant cauſe</hi> among us.</p>
            <p>Do not <hi>theſe things</hi> call <hi>aloud</hi> for <hi>earneſt</hi> endeavours of peace and unity, <hi>eſpecially</hi> and <hi>primarily</hi> among the <hi>orthodox</hi> and <hi>Godly,</hi> which will never be effected, without <hi>moderation,</hi> and that <hi>indifferently</hi> on every hand, whereby <hi>each</hi> may <hi>modeſtly</hi> retain their different apprehenſions in leſſer matters, yet <hi>affectionately</hi> and <hi>mutually</hi> ſubmit and condeſcend in the fear of God, ſo as to <hi>pity</hi> each others <hi>infirmities,</hi> and <hi>jointly amitably ſtrive together</hi> (in Gods way) for the faith and holineſs of the Goſpel, againſt groſs deluſions and profaneneſs, which both abound among us. As my own temper tells me, ſo my knowledge of the dispoſition of many of thoſe called <hi>Independents, Anabaptiſts, &amp;c.</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades me, that ſuch a cloſure is attainable: wherein others diſcompliance hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, let that with the iſſues of it be on them, mean while I think this a fit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb facs="tcp:119445:3"/>
humbly to expreſs my thoughts which are not new: that the interest of <hi>all theſe equally,</hi> with the intereſt of Religion <hi>among all,</hi> lies in mutual modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherein I have <hi>miſſed it,</hi> or been <hi>defective</hi> in this ſhort <hi>Eſſay</hi> upon ſome <hi>few</hi> particulars now in queſtion, I crave pardon of the ſober and judicious, but not of the <hi>cenſuring captious</hi> ſpirit of this Age, that delights to fiſh in <hi>troubled</hi> waters, and to whom <hi>moderation</hi> is a crime. The grave <hi>Oratour</hi> ſuſpected that he had ſpoken ſomething <hi>amiſs,</hi> when at the end he heard the <hi>lauding acclamations</hi> of the <hi>vulgar:</hi> and our Saviour pronounces a Wo to him of whom <hi>all men</hi> ſpeak well: wherefore not valuing this, I thought it my duty <hi>at this time</hi> to ſpeak, though I ſhould do <hi>little more</hi> than audibly pronounce the [Word] <hi>moderation,</hi> yet I ſhould have been glad ſome abler precurſor might have foreſtalled, anticipated me in my deſired retirement.</p>
            <p>If my <hi>conceſſions</hi> of the <hi>faults</hi> of any are beyond their <hi>own convictions,</hi> I hope they will be ſatisfied that none will think that I ſhould be able to ſpeak for others ſo well as they for themſelves, nor is it fit for me to ſpeak my utmoſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of brevity and inoffenſiveneſs. Finally, for my part I neither <hi>deſign</hi> nor <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> the advance of any of my opinion above others, but onely that <hi>moderation</hi> in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 5. as it is render'd in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Annotations, <hi>Equity or equal carriage towards all,</hi> which is the <hi>undoubted</hi> way to beal <hi>all</hi> our breaches, and make us yet an <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> Nation, among whom God may yet delight to dwell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 23. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Which is the deſire, prayer, and poor endeavour of <hi>S. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119445:3"/>
            <head>Moderation, or Arguments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives tending thereunto, Humbly tendred to the Honourable MEMBERS of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the ſaying of a Counſellour to <hi>James</hi> the fifth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (as a <hi>Preludium</hi> to his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Moderation) <hi>[That it was then their happineſs, the meaneſt Subject might freely ſpeak unto their Sovereign.]</hi> Yet do I not adventure to ſpeak to you as a <hi>Collective Body</hi> in your <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign State,</hi> but in an <hi>individual perſonal</hi> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, as Members thereof. Pardon therefore my humble boldneſs, that in this way, and upon this occaſion and ſubject I addreſs my ſelf to your <hi>Honours,</hi> being the more induced by that prudent Dictate of <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Verulam, That the wiſeſt Princes need not think it any diminution to their greatneſs, nor derogation to their ſufficiency to hearken to, and rely upon counſel.</hi> The Argument and ſubject treated of will (I am ſure) <hi>apologize</hi> for it ſelf<hi>: meekneſs, temperance,</hi> and <hi>moderation</hi> being ſuch virtues, that (whether <hi>natural, moral,</hi> or <hi>ſpiritual)</hi> are highly accepted of God, approved of men, and againſt which there is no <hi>Law, Gal.</hi> 5. 23. Never any Age or Nation needed it, and groaned under the defect thereof more than this. Were it more in the hearts, tongues, and pens of men of all ſorts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, <hi>England</hi> might be as happy a People as any under Heaven; which now being a Nation ſadly divided againſt it ſelf cannot bear up long in this epidemical Diſtemper, (without a ſpeedy Remedy) from ſinking into aſhes.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119445:4"/>
where there is biting and devouring one of another, (by <hi>ſecret whiſpers, evil ſurmiſes, harſh interpretings, and paper incendiaries,)</hi> it tends to a conſuming one of another, and making us a publick ſcorne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 15.</note> yea a prey to Domeſtick and forraign enemies.</p>
            <p>Our malady then is manifeſt, as alſo the mortal and pernicious tendency thereof<hi>:</hi> all ſorts of men concentre and agree in this, <hi>that animoſities and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions are our diſeaſe and will undo us.</hi> And why might not all as eaſily agree in the <hi>remedy?</hi> which when all is done will be found to be <hi>Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cruſhing of <hi>this Sect,</hi> and the violent ſubduing <hi>of that ſort,</hi> which many hot and haſty ſpirits cry out for, as that which will mend all, would prove a remedy worſe than the diſeaſe, tempting and provoking every man (judging his own opinions <hi>right,</hi> and his <hi>right</hi> to be free from others impoſing) to lift up his hand againſt his neighbour, and render our wound more incurable. I cannot here forbear citing that paſſage of a very learned man, <hi>It was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a notable obſervation of a wiſe Father, and no leſs ingenuouſly confeſſed, [That thoſe which held and perſwaded preſſure of conſciences were commonly intereſſed therein themſelves, for their own ends.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religion and Reaſon, the Spirit of Chriſt and the Goſpel ſhould rather be hearkened unto, who all offer and uſher in this remedy of <hi>Moderation,</hi> ſo that it needs not any Epiſtle of commendation. And, did we ſtrive to approve our ſelves Chriſtians, we ſhould ſtrive who ſhould excel in this vertue and work. How can this be put <hi>in uſe,</hi> without ſome <hi>Publique Phiſicians of value to be as Hee-goats before the flock, leading Moderators?</hi> And who ſhould be the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derators</hi> in theſe our publick diſcords, but you our <hi>Senators?</hi> and where ſhould you begin with <hi>Moderation,</hi> if not at your own hearts and houſe, in the caſes depending before you concerning Military Officers and other Gentlemen who have acted in your Interval.</p>
            <p>Surely the more cordial, voluntary and extenſive, you are herein, the more honourable<hi>:</hi> and I hope it may not be conſtrued as a limiting or preſcribing to propoſe, <hi>that now it may be written upon you in legible characters, ſo as to be read and known to all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this propoſal come from an obſcure perſon, yet it is from one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſted, and who among others of your Subjects did diſguſt and ill reſent the Act of your late interruption, with all the preceding occaſions thereof; hoping your receſſion (which is now effected) might moſt effectually tend to our common ſafety and ſettlement: which, as it is my deſire and prayer (with ſubmiſſion to the will of God) ſo that my endeavours may be ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, I humbly propoſe theſe few following <hi>healing conſiderations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although it be but a mite, and like the Goats-hair to the publick work of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> yet its offered not with any willingneſs to go beyond my line or ſphere, nor preſumption to be wiſer than my teachers, and therefore hope I ſhall not hereby make my ſelfe a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey<hi>:</hi> as I do it with much ſubmiſſion, ſo without the leaſt intent (God knoweth) of imputation or evil reflection on any hand, that may any way interfere with my preſent aim of <hi>Moderation,</hi> in order to which I humbly offer.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>That humility is the direct and only way to honour, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 12. It is a badge of honour in it ſelf, and in the acceptation of men, the path ordained of God, and pointed out with his finger to be bleſſed with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119445:4"/>
that which is truely honour, rooted in the inward affections and eſtimations of men. This is applyed as adapting for the great work in your hands, <hi>which is to deliver the Iſland,</hi> Job 22. 29, 30. <hi>God hath ſtained the pride of many pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick perſons in this Nation, ſhewing himſelf to be above them.</hi> Wherefore having by a ſtrange providence once more inveſted you with power, <hi>Behold the goodneſs and ſeverity of God, and be not high minded but fear,</hi> Rom. 11. 20, 22. <hi>God ſitteth with an inſpicious eye among the Gods, who ſhall dye like men, and ſhall fall like one of the Princes,</hi> [or like other Princes] <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 7. <hi>When Ephraim ſpake trembling, he exalted himſelf in Iſrael,</hi> Hoſ. 13. 1. <hi>but when he did otherwiſe he dyed,</hi> like as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> for his loftineſs was ſent ſeven years grazing among the Brutes, till he had learned to acknowledge <hi>that God ruled in the Kingdomes of men, and pulled down and ſet up whom it pleaſed him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>Nor is <hi>Humility</hi> ſo excellent, but that <hi>Meekneſs, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Clemency</hi> (whether reckoned concomitants or fruits thereof) they do bear an excellent <hi>proportion</hi> with it, to the adorning of them in whom they are found. What greater argument then that <hi>they are in the ſight of God of great price?</hi> who hath therefore inſtructed Rulers, <hi>that its their glory to paſs over a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> Prov. 19. 11, 12. <hi>And the throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed, as by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo by mercy,</hi> Prov. 20. 28. <hi>But without mercy, ſuch ſhall have judgement without mercy,</hi> Jam. 2. 13.</p>
               <p>This is the more magnified and thank-worthy, by how much there is an opinion of advantage and opportunity for the contrary, and indeed this is moſt like God himſelf, the ſimilitude and imitation of whom is one principal reaſon why Rulers are <hi>called Gods,</hi> who in this ſhould be publick patterns and examples to the world, and eſpecially in this iron age and Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>Nor are thoſe vertues more worthy, valuable, venerable, then <hi>exceſſive anger, wrath, revenge</hi> are the contrary. A <hi>precipitant ſpirit</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hit the mark, nor do the buſineſs. Examples are infinite, that it hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to ſuch actions and iſſues in haſte, by changing times, perſons, laws, as hath been repented of at leaſure, proving unretractable, beyond firſt intentions or expectations<hi>:</hi> God would make the paſſionate Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> know, <hi>that he was not in the whirlwind, nor in the thunder, but in the ſtill and ſoft voice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when the Diſciples would needs have had fire from heaven upon thoſe <hi>who followed not with them,</hi> our Saviour inſtructs them in the ſame leſſon, <hi>[You know not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what ſpirit you are of.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And above all doth it leaſt become grave <hi>Senatours</hi> to do any thing in rage and raſhneſs, witneſs that remarkable example of good <hi>Moſes,</hi> Pſal. 106. 32, 33. That albeit its only noted he <hi>ſpake</hi> unadviſedly with his lips, and although <hi>the people angred him,</hi> and <hi>[they] provoked his ſpirit,</hi> yet it went ill with <hi>Moſes</hi> for <hi>[their]</hi> ſakes<hi>:</hi> this <hi>one</hi> haſty, angry act, judicially deveſted him of his dignity, occaſioned his fall and death in the wilderneſs, and miſſing <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although rigour and ſeverity may ſometimes be termed juſtice, and done for ſecurity from like actions; yet there is need of care, that <hi>revenge</hi> be not in the <hi>root,</hi> nor yet <hi>Lextalionis</hi> the <hi>rule</hi> of ſuch proceedings, nor rigour to be uſed in all caſes till favour hath been tryed to effect the ſame juſt end, <hi>for the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God,</hi> Jam. 1. 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>An opinion of ſome kind of victory and conqueſt, may have a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119445:5"/>
potent influence to ſcrew up the minds of men to a more then ordinary rigour towards the conquered, either in order to their own triumph, or their ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: may it not be ſaid, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> in another caſe? <hi>ſuch glorying is not good;</hi> and Events have oft-times proved it ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charron</hi> tells us not untruely, <hi>the greateſt conqueſt in the world is that of a mans ſelf, gaining Government and dominion over his own paſſions</hi> and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<hi>:</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> avoucheth it, <hi>that he that ruleth his ſpirit is better than the mighty, and doth more than he that takes a City,</hi> Prov. 16. 32. Had <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> done this one exploit, it would have rendred his name more worthy than his conqueſt of the world<hi>:</hi> As it did that <hi>Heathen King,</hi> who in his tont hearing one of his own Souldiers without in the Camp reproaching him, <hi>only bid him go further off, leſt the King ſhould hear him.</hi> Such forgiving and paſſing over injuries (ſaith one well) <hi>ſhews a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">According to <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>mind planted above them and beyond their reach:</hi> Many Princes, not thus conquering themſelves in the way of their <hi>Paſſions,</hi> have ſoon, and before they have been aware, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed themſelves in the way of their <hi>Intereſt.</hi> Governours and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being ordained of God to curb the exorbitant luſts of men, ſhould begin at home, and not ſuffer any thing in <hi>themſelves</hi> to ſwell beyond the regiment of <hi>Reaſon and Moderation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this Section with a paſſage of a wiſe man in like caſe, <hi>Its an aſſured ſign of a worthy and generous ſpirit whom honour amends; for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is or ſhould be the place of vertue: and as in nature things move violently to their place: ſo do they move calmely in their place,</hi> ſo let it be with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>The conſideration of <hi>Viciſſitude</hi> I conceive not unſeaſonable nor impertinent in this matter; nothing being more notoriouſly obvious in our dayes, then that all things under the Sun are ſubject to <hi>changes and mutations.</hi> This makes one ſay pithily, <hi>All knowledge is but remembrance.</hi> Another, <hi>All novelty is but oblivion:</hi> agreeable to <hi>Salom, there is nothing new:</hi> the moral of all is this; that ſeeing all things are in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3. 15.</note> a tickle tottering revolving poſture, and that Government and Governours are ſubject to flux and reflux: moving too and fro: run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the circle as much as any other things, that therefore nothing be done upon an opinion, <hi>that the mountain is ſo ſtrong that it cannot be removed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which is a dayly object to the eye, ſhould be dayly in the mind: <hi>that that ſpoak of the wheel that is now up, is by and by down again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this obſervation made the <hi>vanquiſhed King rejoyce</hi> when he was drawing the Chariot of his <hi>Conquerour,</hi> becauſe it ſhewed him a poſſibility of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, ſo ſhould it make others in proſperity <hi>humbly fear,</hi> in order to their <hi>judging as they would be judged, and meting</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math</hi> 7. 1, 2. <hi>Judges</hi> 1. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>that meaſure unto others they would ſhould be meaſured to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to provoke to</hi> which, <hi>Adonibezek</hi> is a pregnant example, and that Emperour upon whom that obſervation aforeſaid had ſuch an influence.</p>
               <p>Neither is it enough to look at the <hi>outward wheels,</hi> but alſo at the <hi>wheel of Gods Providence within the wheels,</hi> Ezek. 1. 16. this tends to moderate the heart under all <hi>changes,</hi> and puts upon enquiry what God teaches by every turn. Thus <hi>David,</hi> not terminating his obſervation upon <hi>Shimei</hi> that curſed him, but elevating his mind above the inſtrument, ſaith, <hi>It may be the Lord</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119445:5"/>
                  <hi>ſent him to curſe me this day,</hi> 2 Sam. 16. 9, 10, 11. and thereupon forbore to puniſh him, though by many about him he was earneſtly incited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> Iſa. 10. 9, 10, 11. reckoning and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting himſelf above all providential <hi>viciſſitude,</hi> boaſts thus, <hi>Is not Calno as Charchemiſh? is not Hamath as Arpad? is not Samaria as Damaſcus? as I have done unto Samaria and her Idols, ſhall I not do unto Jeruſalem and her Idols?</hi> not conſidering the <hi>ſtern</hi> of all affaires to be in Gods hand, and that he was now to deal with <hi>Gods people, whom though under ſin,</hi> yet God would not utterly forſake. <hi>It greatly alters the caſe when we deal with good men though ſuppoſed erring, yea though really erring.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>Shall I crave leave to paſs from theſe <hi>premiſed Generals</hi> to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more <hi>particular</hi> relating to the reputed fault of thoſe who are now under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt: who are of two ſorts, either ſuch who acted in the <hi>Interruption,</hi> or ſuch who only acted in ſome publick affairs in the <hi>Interval</hi> of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>Firſt, not to eſpouſe or juſtifie the fact of interrupting, nor yet to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with the cauſes or occaſions of jealouſies and offences, real or ſuppoſed, given or taken any way: yet I hope I may without offence tenderly touch the circumſtances, being ſimply in order to my aim of <hi>Moderation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To go no farther back then that Act of Parliament made <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. Let it firſt be ſuppoſed thereupon, that the Officers of the Army did accompt of themſelves as <hi>harſhly and ſeverely</hi> dealt withall, by the ſaid Act, <hi>Vacating</hi> ſo many Commiſſions, <hi>Altering</hi> ſo greatly the Conduct of the Army, <hi>Ejecting</hi> nine of the old conſiderable Officers: yet do I not hereupon ſay they ſhould do as they did, put a force upon the houſe: ſuch caſes are very tender. Its a received maxime, <hi>the beſt Counſels may erre; yet Parliaments are the higheſt Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſels</hi> (though ſome judged this not to be ſo.) And therefore although the Officers might think and revolve in their minds, that they were lately inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of introducing this Parliament to a <hi>reſeſſion,</hi> though not giving the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>right,</hi> yet the <hi>opportunity</hi> of ſitting, that they had <hi>ſerved</hi> them faithfully, and lately againſt their enemies both old and new, that they were free from all <hi>fore intentions</hi> of force towards the Parliament; according to the <hi>jealouſies</hi> they deemed unduely conceived of them, that they feared the altering of the conduct of the Army might tend to deſtroy the only outward ſence againſt the old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated enemy, <hi>by a gradual change of the whole,</hi> and thereby in a little time <hi>endanger their common cauſe.</hi> All theſe and more ſuch like conſiderations might have been in a fair and ſubmiſſive way tendered to <hi>an uninterrupted houſe,</hi> with a deſire of a favourable hearing, and then ſubmitted to their final judgement: but ſuch a hearing not being <hi>fore provided</hi> and <hi>prepropoſed,</hi> and they diſpairing of obtaining it, by obſerving the preparations made, and making for the forcible and preſent execution of the ſaid act, and ſuppoſing ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences to their cauſe, as well as perſons, might and would enſue, (as hath by them been alledged) did thus proceed to put it upon the iſſue of an <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi> How far this <hi>fact</hi> was <hi>faulty,</hi> is not now a ſeaſon to <hi>aggravate,</hi> nor yet how far in any reſpects it might be <hi>venial.</hi> I ſubmit the whole thus ſtated to the remembrance of all perſons any way concerned, to make the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement thereof to <hi>Moderation,</hi> ſave only (not to judge the Parliaments Act and Judgment, yet were it not beyond the ſeaſon I might humbly offer) that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119445:6"/>
it was the ſober opinion of <hi>not a few</hi> at that time, that ſuch a <hi>hearing</hi> of thoſe Officers aforeſaid, might probably without any inconveniency have produced and preſerved a good underſtanding, and prevented all the evils ſuppoſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the defect thereof<hi>:</hi> how far this may be argumentative now to <hi>Moderate,</hi> I only mention it, and ſubmit it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>But may there not be many things fit for <hi>after conſideration</hi> tending hereunto? admit the fact <hi>Exorbitant,</hi> yet may not their <hi>ends</hi> therein be <hi>publick, juſt and good,</hi> and not <hi>ſiniſter private nor injurious unto any?</hi> that there may be <hi>good intentions,</hi> where there may be <hi>obliquity</hi> in ſome proſecuting <hi>actions,</hi> is a thing <hi>indubitable;</hi> to believe they were <hi>ſuch</hi> here, by thoſe who know the perſons well, is I think groundedly <hi>charitable;</hi> to inſiſt upon <hi>ends and deſigns,</hi> to that <hi>uſe and end</hi> for which I urge them, will I ſuppoſe in the cloſe be judged <hi>reaſonable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That then they did not do this from <hi>revenge,</hi> nor aſpiring after <hi>ſole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or domination,</hi> nor being unwilling to be <hi>ſubject</hi> ſo they might be <hi>ſafe,</hi> much leſs out of any intent to <hi>ſubvert the Magiſtracy or Miniſtry</hi> of the Nation, nor overthrow <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> as ſome ungroundedly ſuggeſt, that they did not do it upon the pretended <hi>Munſter Spirit,</hi> nor in purſuance of any <hi>Euthufiaſtical, Prophetick, Fanatick</hi> opinions of any <hi>peculiar divine right,</hi> that <hi>they or any</hi> have to civil Government, but as members of the Nation, having been long embarqued under the greateſt obligations in a <hi>Common cauſe,</hi> wherein, among other things, <hi>civil and Religious liberty</hi> for all who live honeſt, godly and peaceable of all perſwaſions is involved; apprehending that in ſome hazard of a ſhipwrack, (I ſay not groundedly) were led hereunto, thus far their own plea to all which profeſſions of theirs, it may be hard to gain the credit of ſuch readers, who are prejudiced by looking on them through the red glaſs of miſrepreſentations, and know not the perſons, nor their or any of their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, Piety and Morality</hi> in their <hi>private Converſations, Church-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or family behaviours</hi> towards God and their neighbour, wherein it muſt be affirmed from undoubted knowledge, for many years paſt to this day, that moſt of them <hi>do excel in Vertue,</hi> and that from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Orthodox principles</hi> of the Chriſtian Religion, generally received and acknowledged to be ſuch.</p>
               <p>Now although all this (ſuppoſed true) doth not <hi>juſtific</hi> this act, nor do I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to that end, yet doth it wipe off the dirt of thoſe calumnies, alſo <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate</hi> the fault, upon the ſame reaſon that they are alledged to increaſe it, and abate and diminiſh the <hi>aggravations,</hi> with a <hi>reference</hi> to theſe perſons; and conſequently render them (if not the more <hi>deſerving,</hi> yet) the more <hi>fit</hi> for favour and free impunity.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſhut up this Section with that adviſement of a prudent writer<hi>: One ſpecial remedy againſt exceſſive anger, is to ſever the conſtruction of the injury from the point of contempt, imputing it to miſunderſtanding, fear, or other paſſions and infirmities, what you will.</hi> Sir <hi>Fra. Bacons</hi> Eſſaies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>The various and manifold <hi>turnings</hi> and <hi>revolutions</hi> in <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> for many years together in this Nation, made and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to be made, by <hi>other hands</hi> and <hi>heads</hi> beſides theirs of the Army, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the manifold <hi>violent claims</hi> of divers and contrary parties and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts to the <hi>Sovereign Rule</hi> of very late days, ſeveral of whom <hi>menacing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand a Ravelling out and Reverting all,</hi> to the firſt ſtate of affairs before
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119445:6"/>
the War began, to the loſs of all theſe twenty years Conteſt. All this renders the <hi>Fact</hi> it ſelf, and conſequently the reputed <hi>Fault</hi> thereof the more <hi>disputable</hi> and <hi>doubtfull</hi> to many judicious men, and doubtleſs not plainly a Fault to the judgements and conſciences of thoſe eſpecially concerned therein<hi>:</hi> whereas in other manifeſt faults, it may be well preſumed, that moſt of the ſame perſons would avoid doing the <hi>leaſt</hi> apparant known evil, to obtain the greateſt good unto themſelves; <hi>neither is this urged at random.</hi> And if all <hi>advantages</hi> ſhould be taken upon an exact diſquiſition and marking all that hath been <hi>done amiſs</hi> of this kinde, what ſort of men will not be <hi>culpable,</hi> and ſome way or other <hi>obnoxious</hi> both to <hi>cenſure</hi> and <hi>danger?</hi> If therefore they be <hi>allowed</hi> but the ſame <hi>grains</hi> for their infirmities with <hi>other</hi> men, then their falling <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>lateſt</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eye and hand of offence might not augment their <hi>cenſure,</hi> but in ſtead thereof there would be room for <hi>Moderation,</hi> which teacheth (among other) this wholeſom Leſſon,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>That wherein all their errours have,</l>
                  <l>Let all ſorts pardon give, and pardon crave.</l>
               </q>
               <p>It being alſo notorious how <hi>little</hi> the <hi>publick Pulſe</hi> did beat towards the late Return, and how <hi>much</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> of this <hi>Parliament</hi> is diſavowed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached by publick Prints that freely and currantly paſs up and down City and Countrey, imputing as <hi>great,</hi> yea <hi>greater Extraordinaries</hi> and <hi>Exorbitancies</hi> unto them than thoſe now in queſtion; alſo avowing the hoſtile undertakings of Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> as moſt worthy upon that account, for the introduction of a <hi>free</hi> and <hi>full Parliament,</hi> the cogency of whoſe Plea I meddle not withall, but upon a ſuppoſition of their prevailing, many may be accounted to ſtand in as much need as others of <hi>moderation</hi> and <hi>indemnity.</hi> And whether it may be <hi>denied</hi> them, the Lord knows, things being on the reverting hand, God knows where they will ſtop and ſtand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>The <hi>manner</hi> of their managing this <hi>Revolution,</hi> is not inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>mitigation</hi> of the <hi>fault;</hi> for as much as both in the Act of <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> as alſo in the proſecution in all other parts and places both North and South, they have uſed all poſſible care to avoid and prevent the <hi>leaſt</hi> drop of <hi>blood</hi> in the <hi>Conteſt,</hi> wherein the providence of God hath eminently concurred thereby, <hi>as with a finger</hi> pointing out <hi>Moderation.</hi> How <hi>backward</hi> have they been to <hi>action,</hi> how forward to admit of delays, how ready for any amica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Conferences</hi> in order to a <hi>right</hi> underſtanding and <hi>peaceable</hi> accord. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, their indulgent reſpects towards both <hi>Parliament Members</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Officers,</hi> not <hi>ſeizing</hi> and <hi>ſecuring</hi> their perſons, when it was in the power of their hand to do it: yet they rock not thoſe <hi>advantages</hi> they had and might have had (as well as others) to purſue their buſineſs, had they been diſpoſed to <hi>violence</hi> in thoſe reſpects. All which, as it doth from God, ſo from them beſpeak <hi>tenderneſs</hi> and <hi>moderation</hi> towards their <hi>perſons, families, friends.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
               <p>Neither may it be forgotten the <hi>generally acknowledged</hi> faithfull and eminent <hi>Services</hi> they have done both formerly and lately for this <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and the <hi>Nation;</hi> which is more a <hi>Plea</hi> in the preſent <hi>Caſe</hi> than in many other; becauſe (among other things) it was an <hi>opinion</hi> in <hi>them</hi> of an <hi>ill requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119445:7"/>
for all thoſe <hi>ſervices,</hi> burying them with their names under <hi>infamy,</hi> that did precede and provoke unto the <hi>fault,</hi> which whether it excuſe or not, yet it freeth it from ſome aggravation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> And whereas <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 1. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. will and may be objected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet let me ſay, It is one thing for a man to <hi>apoſtatize,</hi> ſo as to depart from all righteouſneſs, to <hi>violate</hi> manifeſt morals, another thing for a man to <hi>erre</hi> in ſome <hi>one</hi> act, and that act ſo <hi>circumſtantiated</hi> as it is; for <hi>now</hi> in our times, moſt ſorts of men think it not unrighteous to attempt the <hi>ſole</hi> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Soveraign power,</hi> wherein <hi>theſe</hi> poſſibly may reckon upon a <hi>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhare,</hi> as <hi>much,</hi> if not <hi>more</hi> then many others, having been <hi>ſo long,</hi> and <hi>ſo much</hi> engaged under <hi>Parliamentary authority</hi> in the greateſt hazards, above others, to obtain a <hi>certain ſecurity</hi> to the Nations and themſelves, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of their properties and juſt liberties, and yet far from <hi>deſigning</hi> to abridge or oppreſs others in matters <hi>Religious</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> (as by-paſt time witneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th) wherein others <hi>threaten</hi> to abridge and oppreſs them if uppermoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</head>
               <p>Eſpecially this being added, that their <hi>revolving</hi> was not a <hi>revolt</hi> from the <hi>main cauſe</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> of the Nation to eſpouſe another of a reputed enemy, either Domeſtick or forraign, as many others have done both <hi>formerly</hi> and <hi>lately;</hi> now <hi>Moderation</hi> will conſider <hi>others</hi> faults <hi>negatively what they are not,</hi> rather then <hi>poſitively what they are:</hi> and it is ſuppoſed their <hi>fault</hi> will not be <hi>greater,</hi> or receive a <hi>greater</hi> ſentence, becauſe not of that kind.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſeeing they remain <hi>embarqued</hi> in the ſame <hi>bottome</hi> with all others concerned as firme as ever, though they may have <hi>erred</hi> in the agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and proſecution of the ſame <hi>publick ends,</hi> (as who have not?) why may it not be deemed and adjudged an errour of the <hi>right hand,</hi> and imputed to their <hi>frailty,</hi> and not their <hi>malice,</hi> and therefore to be <hi>reſtored with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of meekneſs,</hi> all being ſubject to temptation? <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1, 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</head>
               <p>As touching thoſe <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who in the late <hi>Interval</hi> did <hi>act</hi> in <hi>publick capacities,</hi> either the <hi>Committee of Safety</hi> or in <hi>Militia's,</hi> upon <hi>new Summons; Commiſſions,</hi> &amp;c. of theſe whether any did <hi>deſignedly</hi> reſiſt the Parliaments <hi>Reſtitution</hi> I know not, yet if any ſuch be, they may not have <hi>outacted</hi> the <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>full in indempni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> upon all the <hi>Conſiderations</hi> aforeſaid. But poſſibly <hi>all</hi> or moſt of them, did but meerly <hi>aym</hi> and <hi>act</hi> for the preſent <hi>preſervation of the publick peace</hi> and <hi>ſafety</hi> of the <hi>whole,</hi> in an <hi>Inter regnum,</hi> and time of <hi>common danger.</hi> This is offered not only as <hi>poſſible,</hi> but <hi>well known</hi> of ſundry ſober and judicious perſons, and may of others be <hi>preſumed,</hi> that they <hi>deſigned</hi> nothing directly againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but only whiles <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> were out of <hi>courſe,</hi> did endeavour to keep all from <hi>ſinking</hi> into a <hi>Chaos</hi> of <hi>confuſion,</hi> to which the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the people ſeemed to tend by a direct oppoſition to you. Now it hath been accompted a warrantable <hi>ground</hi> and laudable rule of <hi>action,</hi> to take <hi>Affairs</hi> in their preſent <hi>conſtitution</hi> (however they came ſo) and to put a helping hand or ſhoulder upon a <hi>publick ſummons</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all the <hi>evil,</hi> and uſher in all the <hi>good</hi> that may be.</p>
               <p>Upon which accompt it is ſuppoſed (no other ſubſtantial ground being known) many of the honourable <hi>Members</hi> of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> have <hi>ſate</hi> as <hi>Members</hi> upon new <hi>Elections</hi> in ſome of thoſe <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119445:7"/>
have <hi>intervened</hi> their firſt <hi>interruption</hi> in 1653. and their firſt <hi>reſeſſion</hi> on <hi>May</hi> 7. 1659. and done many other <hi>publick actions,</hi> which at one ſtep farther may be poſſibly reckoned equal with this in hand.</p>
               <p>If ſome few particular <hi>perſons</hi> have <hi>reſerved</hi> themſelves meerly <hi>paſſive</hi> and <hi>neutral</hi> in all <hi>changes,</hi> they beſt know whether their grounds and ends were <hi>private</hi> or <hi>publick, ſufficient</hi> or <hi>formalities,</hi> but that <hi>ſort</hi> or <hi>Sect</hi> of men throughout the three Nations that ſhall plead <hi>not guilty,</hi> may throw <hi>the firſt stone,</hi> and try whether it will not <hi>recoyle</hi> and <hi>rebound</hi> firſt upon them. Let <hi>ſuch</hi> alſo be added to theſe, who have been <hi>forward</hi> at ſuch times for <hi>publick</hi> action without <hi>publick Summons, Commiſſions,</hi> &amp;c. for ſome third intereſt, and then upon a ſcrutinous <hi>ſubſtraction,</hi> there will be very few found to be employed in the <hi>lateſt turn</hi> without oblivion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 13.</head>
               <p>And as it is judged <hi>reaſonable,</hi> that theſe nor none of theſe (above due proportion and equality) ſhould fare the worſe, becauſe they are of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> opinion about ſome <hi>inſtituted</hi> parts of Religion, ſo much leſs ſhould there be in any, <hi>an ill opinion,</hi> or an <hi>ill aſpect</hi> towards thoſe people, who in ſome <hi>ſuch</hi> matters of Religion (far remote from, and forraign unto all conteſts about civil Government) may <hi>agree</hi> with theſe, or ſome <hi>few</hi> of <hi>theſe perſons,</hi> who may be the <hi>objects</hi> of diſpleaſure, foraſmuch as theſe people and congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with all peaceableneſs (attending only their religious concerns and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their places) have been and are <hi>unconcerned</hi> in theſe <hi>tranſactions,</hi> as much as if <hi>none</hi> of their <hi>perſwaſion</hi> did at all intermeddle with them. What therefore hath been done by any of thoſe called <hi>Independents</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts among many others</hi> in the Army, hath not been as they were <hi>Members</hi> of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> congregation, but as <hi>Members</hi> of the Nation, not aiming at any <hi>peculiar benefits,</hi> but the enjoying of a <hi>publick, common right of equal ſafety and liberty, with all others in theſe Nations,</hi> which muſt be acknowledged to be more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to <hi>danger</hi> in all hands then the <hi>right</hi> of moſt others, whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> may be more approximate and coherent with the ſpirit of the people in general. Let me herein not be underſtood to gird thoſe call'd <hi>of the national way,</hi> but only moderately to expoſtulate with thoſe, who are ſober and godly of them. Are not, or may not ſuch be <hi>ſecure</hi> from all <hi>fears</hi> of <hi>perſecution</hi> in all <hi>changes?</hi> do they not in that reſpect <hi>pitch</hi> upon their <hi>feet</hi> in every turn<hi>:</hi> if therefore they aſpire <hi>ſole</hi> and <hi>Supreme rule,</hi> have not godly diſſenters grounds to <hi>fear,</hi> that its for <hi>impoſing</hi> on <hi>others,</hi> more then ſimply for <hi>ſelf ſecurity.</hi> I grant there is two <hi>national wayes</hi> of <hi>worſhip</hi> in <hi>conteſt</hi> againſt <hi>each other,</hi> which ſhould teach them both <hi>Moderation</hi> towards <hi>ſober diſſenters</hi> from <hi>both,</hi> ſeeing they are each <hi>diſſenters</hi> from the other, but both concurring againſt the third<hi>:</hi> muſt it not be rationally acknowledg'd, that there is a <hi>grounded provocation</hi> of this third ſort to ſtrive and contend for their <hi>equal right</hi> in their <hi>native country.</hi> I conſent, that they ſhould ſtrive lawfully in their places. and ſo ſhould others as much, but if any of them <hi>erre</hi> herein, muſt it not be <hi>conceded</hi> that they are upon <hi>diſadvantages</hi> in ſome reſpects <hi>more</hi> than others, which doth plead <hi>more</hi> for their <hi>indempnity.</hi> But would it not be <hi>more ſafe</hi> for <hi>all</hi> theſe ſorts, who agree in the <hi>main foundation, principles of Chriſtian Religion,</hi> to underſtand and diſcharge each other from all jealouſies of Impoſition, that <hi>all</hi> may ſit down <hi>ſafely</hi> in their <hi>rights,</hi> and under their <hi>vines</hi> and <hi>fig-trees,</hi> none making them or any of them afraid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119445:8"/>
                  <hi>Interim,</hi> Its then very <hi>undue</hi> to attribute all our diſturbances and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions unto thoſe called <hi>Independents, Anabaptiſts</hi> indefinitly, as <hi>too</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly it is. Whereas its well known by all, who addict themſelves to a <hi>right underſtanding</hi> of what they affirme, that generally they in their ſeveral <hi>congregations,</hi> do attend only ſuch things as are appropriate to their religious worſhip and Chriſtian edifying. And other ſorts of men (whom for Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake (which is my only work and end) I ſhall not name) have done that againſt authoritie, <hi>yea</hi> againſt this conſtitution of <hi>Parliament</hi> more deſerving theſe imputations. Neither is this a <hi>new</hi> or <hi>ſtrange</hi> thing for men by <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictions</hi> to lay their <hi>own</hi> faults wholly on <hi>others</hi> ſhoulders, <hi>for Ahab could call Elijah the troubler of Iſrael, when as Elijah juſtly retorts it upon himſelf,</hi> 1 King. 18. 18, 19. I ſpeak not this (the Lord knoweth) from the <hi>leaſt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>Envy,</hi> for I am <hi>ſincerely</hi> bent for <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> and do highly eſteem and honour the <hi>ſober and godly</hi> of all theſe perſwaſions, but that no perſons <hi>forgetting themſelves,</hi> may <hi>uncharitably vaunt,</hi> and lift up themſelves and ſtir up others againſt thoſe, who, holding <hi>Orthodox principles,</hi> deſire to <hi>fear God</hi> and live <hi>peaceably</hi> in the land, in <hi>lawful ſubjection</hi> to juſt authorities that are or ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>How far yours and publick intereſt, if <hi>duely</hi> weighed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted (upon a preſumption its not changed) doth lye in this of <hi>Moderation</hi> being a tender point, I ſhall <hi>now</hi> much forbear the enquiry. Howbeit, though thoſe upon the <hi>hill</hi> may foreſee and deſcry far, yet thoſe who are in the <hi>valley</hi> in dayly converſe with men of all ſorts, are not unacquainted with the <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> of your friends, and the <hi>boaſts</hi> of thoſe who are not your friends, <hi>that like the bleating of the ſheep and lowing of the Oxen, are very ſignificant:</hi> The ejecting old Officers in the three Nations <hi>by hundreds,</hi> many of whom deemed much unconcerned in the late tranſactions, as it is humbly conceived, it tends to diſoblige many faſt friends forward in your late return, ſo alſo doth it not gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the deſires and vivifie the expiring hopes of thoſe, who are no better friends to you than to the Army? touching the tendency of which many <hi>ſubſtantial men</hi> are the more inſpicious, doubting <hi>aſtrenuous</hi> proſecuting of a change may <hi>too</hi> ſuddenly run upon an unſeen <hi>precipice</hi> beyond retreat: and the rather, that whiles the <hi>Aim</hi> in all this may be to <hi>preoccupate</hi> a force on the one hand, other ſorts of men may be <hi>employed,</hi> who in proſecution of their peculiar intereſts<hi>:</hi> may not be to <hi>learn</hi> to employ <hi>force</hi> both upon and againſt <hi>Parliaments, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> this Parliament; and whether upon <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worſe</hi> accompts, I ſpare now to determine, but rather humbly propoſe it as thought adviſeable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo <hi>great</hi> and <hi>general diſlocations</hi> of <hi>able</hi> Officers in <hi>all</hi> parts and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, doth not <hi>tend to tear and rend</hi> your own <hi>intereſt</hi> in pieces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>Moreover it is obſervable and memorable how <hi>able</hi> they have been, not only for <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> in their <hi>Conduct,</hi> but alſo how much of a <hi>good conſcience</hi> they have ſhewn in their <hi>righteous, pious</hi> Government and <hi>diſcipline</hi> of the Army, <hi>ſtrictly</hi> puniſhing and ſuppreſſing all vices, eſpecially theſe <hi>three</hi> moſt incident to Martial bands, <hi>viz. Swearing, violence</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> the <hi>firſt ſin</hi> being more immediately againſt <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> againſt the <hi>neighbour,</hi> the <hi>third</hi> againſt the perſons <hi>themſelves:</hi> by which <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> they have brought and kept the Army in that temperate poſture, as is <hi>famouſly</hi> acknowledged to <hi>ſurpaſs all</hi> the Armyes in the world. That this is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119445:8"/>
already broken and impaired to a great degree (which is great pity) there are ſome inſtances ſuggeſted, and obſerved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>Upon the whole, the greateſt <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>three Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (out of other hands) is now in your hands <hi>to interpret, mannage, and conſerve,</hi> (which taken in general) <hi>it is the common right of all men in their properties and liberties, and the ſpecial countenance, encouragement, and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all who walk in the fear of God, and exerciſe themſelves unto godlineſs, of different perſwaſions, relating to Church-government and diſcipline.</hi> I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propoſe then, that as <hi>righteous, ſolid,</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> men ſeem <hi>onely ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate</hi> and <hi>apt</hi> for ſuch a <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> intereſt; ſo a <hi>moderate, meek,</hi> and <hi>flexible</hi> temper and diſpoſition is a <hi>qualification</hi> as undoubtedly neceſſary for Officers of truſt and power, <hi>conſidering</hi> all thoſe <hi>Differences</hi> among good men throughout theſe three Nations. A <hi>particular intereſt formed</hi> and <hi>framed out</hi> of any <hi>one</hi> of theſe in a <hi>diametrical oppoſition</hi> unto, or upon the <hi>head</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> is humbly conceived to be the ready way to keep open, and make wider the <hi>Wounds</hi> and <hi>Breaches</hi> already made, to <hi>ſtave</hi> off our <hi>Settlement,</hi> if not <hi>aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> diviſions and contentions to the <hi>breaking all.</hi> As publick truſt ſhould be withheld from <hi>profane</hi> men, that may open a Flood-gate for <hi>profaneneſs</hi> and <hi>ungodlineſs</hi> by evil <hi>example</hi> and by a <hi>Law:</hi> (which through the providence and mercy of God hath for many years been kept out to a very great degree,) ſo alſo not put or inveſted in the hand of <hi>violence,</hi> that may prove to any fearing God as the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of a <hi>Bramble:</hi> for although they cannot expect <hi>Grapes from Thorns, nor Figs from Thiſtles,</hi> yet they can look for deliverance and help to come from Heaven ſome other way, from him who is <hi>the hope of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble, and no Rock like this Rock to all that truſt in him, all Enemies themſelves being Judges.</hi> It's deſirable that thoſe that are or may be in Authority may have <hi>that wiſdom of the poor wiſe man whereby to deliver our Iſland and City, Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 15, 16, 17, 18. that making <hi>ſure</hi> of being in the way that God will <hi>bleſs</hi> and not <hi>blow</hi> upon and <hi>blaſt;</hi> good men <hi>of all ſorts</hi> may according to the Rule of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1. not onely <hi>make ſupplications</hi> (according to their duty) but alſo <hi>offer up thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings unto God on their behalf.</hi> Which as it will be the comfort of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſo will it prove the crown and comfort of the Ruler, both now and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>Contrary to the <hi>tenour</hi> of this laſt <hi>Section,</hi> ſome think it the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of God, others the intereſt of the Nation, to ſuppreſs the <hi>Liberties,</hi> if not to deſtroy the <hi>Lives</hi> of a company of people, ſtyled by them <hi>Sectaries,</hi> that is, <hi>Followers,</hi> which name of <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>Sectary</hi> is equally fit for all ſorts, But if it ſhall prove in the iſſue, that they or moſt of them are and aim to be <hi>Followers</hi> of God according to his <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> in <hi>righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eouſneſs</hi> and <hi>true holineſs,</hi> ſurely then it will neither be the intereſt of <hi>God</hi> or of the <hi>Nation,</hi> (admit they do erre, as all others elſe do) to attempt <hi>thus</hi> to uſe them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prove to ſuch as <hi>Christ</hi> foreſheweth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 6. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little ones that believe in me, it were better for him that a Mill-ſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depths of the ſea.</hi> Though they may be but <hi>little ones,</hi> and <hi>weak in faith,</hi> yet <hi>received of God,</hi> and therein not to be <hi>despiſed and judged of men, Rom.</hi> 14. 1, 3. Mr. <hi>Trap</hi> in his <hi>Commentary</hi> upon this place runs thus, Affectu charitatis, <hi>&amp;c. Put him into</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119445:9"/>
                  <hi>your boſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, bear with his weakneſſes, &amp;c. Bucer</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>rejected none, though different in ſome opinions in whom he found,</hi> A liquid Chriſti, <hi>Any thing of Chriſt, whoſe weaklings are to be handled with all tenderneſs.</hi> (And further wittily) <hi>Wring not mens conſciences, you may hap to break the wards if ye do.</hi> And why ſhould this Indulgence be <hi>peculiar</hi> to any ſort? why ſhould that tenderneſs and liberty be doled and diſtributed under the notion of <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>privilege,</hi> which is a <hi>common</hi> and <hi>equal right?</hi> The truth is in <hi>this caſe,</hi> men run the greateſt <hi>hazard</hi> in the world of <hi>fighting</hi> againſt God, and thereby drawing the judgement of God upon themſelves <hi>even</hi> of the <hi>ſame kinde.</hi> For example, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh of <hi>France enters into a League for the extirpation of the Proteſtants, and ſuddenly after the ſame returned heavily upon his own head.</hi> And ſurely there is the <hi>ſame reaſon</hi> to expect it ſo in <hi>England;</hi> if we conſider that thoſe who moſt ſolicit the ſuppreſſion of <hi>Sectaries</hi> are themſelves of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and contrary <hi>Sects</hi> in the external parts of religious worſhip<hi>:</hi> though theſe do <hi>joyntly</hi> declaim a <hi>third</hi> ſort of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who are therefore like the <hi>Sect</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians, Acts</hi> 22. 28. <hi>Every where ſpoken againſt.</hi> This <hi>conjunction</hi> is not from a near <hi>Similitude,</hi> much leſs from an <hi>identity</hi> and <hi>ſameneſs</hi> in external profeſſion of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline</hi> among <hi>themſelves,</hi> but onely from an agreement in <hi>Nega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ives</hi> complicate in a <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>oppoſition,</hi> which when <hi>Poſitives</hi> come in queſtion among <hi>themſelves,</hi> they are no more capable of incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and admixion than Iron and Clay. And if this <hi>third</hi> ſort of <hi>Sectaries</hi> were a ſhort time <hi>dormant,</hi> it would ſoon appear there were <hi>other</hi> ſorts of <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> in <hi>England</hi> by their publick conteſts <hi>as of old.</hi> Is it not then moſt rational and Chriſtian, and moſt <hi>equally</hi> profitable for all, that <hi>all</hi> theſe (in purſuance of the negotiation of worthy Mr. <hi>John Dury)</hi> ſhould <hi>mutually</hi> comply upon fair terms of <hi>Moderation</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>forbearance?</hi> eſpecially being all <hi>embarqued</hi> in <hi>one common Proteſtant Cauſe,</hi> agreeing in the <hi>grand</hi> points and articles of Faith and Doctrine, againſt the common Enemies of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and its pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whether <hi>Pagans, Mahometans, Jews, Papiſts,</hi> or profane perſons; withall conſidering that this <hi>third ſort</hi> have the <hi>ſame native right,</hi> and are <hi>not</hi> an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable intereſt</hi> in the three Nations.</p>
               <p>Theſe things do call <hi>aloud</hi> upon thoſe at <hi>Stern</hi> to <hi>moderate among all,</hi> as they will <hi>ſave</hi> and <hi>heal</hi> a bleeding languiſhing State, from <hi>periſhing</hi> and <hi>ſinking</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>inteſtine</hi> diſcords. <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s indulgence towards thoſe he judged <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> preſerved the unity of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and the peace of the <hi>Empire</hi> and rendred him a worthy <hi>Moderator</hi> at ſeveral turns. And what learned Author, <hi>ancient</hi> or <hi>modern,</hi> or what <hi>ſort</hi> of men will not acknowledge this moſt worthy in the <hi>doctrinal part,</hi> and in their <hi>own caſe,</hi> till being violent and uppermoſt the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng caſe becomes applicable unto <hi>others?</hi> And it muſt be as freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all acquainted with <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that for <hi>one real Heretick</hi> there have been a <hi>thouſand good Chriſtians</hi> deſtroyed by the principle and practice of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, in all Nations and Ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 18</head>
               <p>It is not to be omitted, that albeit the <hi>radical common</hi> ground of endeavours of ſuppreſſing <hi>ſome ſorts,</hi> is <hi>moſtly,</hi> if not <hi>meerly,</hi> their <hi>Religious</hi> opinions, yet the <hi>grand guize</hi> and <hi>vizard</hi> that is commonly put and ſought to be put upon ſuch Deſigns is, a publick pretence of ſome flagitious opinions or crimes of a <hi>civil</hi> kinde and nature, <hi>viz. That they are Enemies to Magiſtracy, Government, &amp;c</hi> The like caſe of <hi>Daniel, chap</hi> 6 4 5. <hi>Then the Princes and</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119445:9"/>
                  <hi>Preſidents ſought to finde occaſion againſt</hi> Daniel, <hi>concerning the Kingdom; but finding none,</hi> v. 5, <hi>Then ſaid they, We ſhall not finde any occaſion againſt this</hi> Daniel, <hi>except we finde it againſt him concerning the Law of his God. Thus</hi> Chriſt <hi>was a reputed Enemy to</hi> Ceſar. <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>in like manner, (with this addition) that he was a mover of ſedition.</hi> Anſwerable to all which, <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Hiſtory</hi> tells us, that when the <hi>Heathen</hi> had a deſign to <hi>cut</hi> the <hi>throats</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> they made their way to it by fomenting and ſpreading this falſe calumnious accuſation, <hi>that the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>intended to cut their throats;</hi> in which caſe I ſuppoſe none will blame the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> if then they ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>anticipate</hi> ſuch a deſign, and <hi>forcibly</hi> defend themſelves from general deſtruction, eſpecially from a <hi>popular Maſſacre,</hi> though countenanced and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the <hi>Magiſtrate, without</hi> interpreting that a reſiſtance of Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of <hi>Magiſtracy. Nay the</hi> Waldenſes <hi>under the Duke of</hi> Savoy <hi>after ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in ſome ſcruple about it by the judgement of their learned Miniſters in the year</hi> 1555. <hi>did martially endeavour to obviate the pernicious Deſign of the Duke, [Acts and Monuments] and the ſame again of late days in</hi> 1655. <hi>upon a new attempt to deſtroy them, as is memorable to all.</hi> The ground and reaſon of all which is rendred by the <hi>Learned, that for as much as protection and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection are reciprocals, where the former is not ſoundly aſſured, or manifeſtly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, the later is relaxed, and not obliging, at leaſt in that natural moral caſe of ſelf-preſervation from publick ruine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I mention not this Poſition as mine <hi>own,</hi> nor with any intent to <hi>prompt</hi> to any diſturbance, nor am I ignorant that <hi>caſes</hi> may <hi>vary</hi> according to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and the point is tender, but my <hi>aim</hi> is, it may be improved to <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> both in <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> in this <hi>Criſis</hi> of our publick affairs, that no ſort of men, (particularly thoſe called <hi>Sectaries)</hi> may be put upon any <hi>tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> through fears of hurt, (which oft times works ſtronger than the feeling) and then blamed and reproached by <hi>thoſe</hi> who put the <hi>temptation</hi> on them, who yet <hi>of all other</hi> in ſuch caſes ſhould <hi>moſt</hi> forbear to blame and reproach; for as much as <hi>thoſe</hi> who put the <hi>temptation</hi> are <hi>parties</hi> in the <hi>fault,</hi> if any happen, and <hi>conſequently</hi> in the <hi>reproach</hi> due thereunto.</p>
               <p>All this I ground upon thoſe <hi>notorious publick</hi> and <hi>general</hi> ſuggeſtions all the Nation over (I cannot but call <hi>calumnies)</hi> againſt thoſe called <hi>Sectaries</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly like that of the <hi>old</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> aforeſaid, which ſeems like the <hi>black cloud of the bigneſs of a mans hand,</hi> to portend a deſigned deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them, <hi>especially</hi> wherein in any <hi>respects,</hi> and in any <hi>places,</hi> they are not detected and ſuppreſt by <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> but <hi>rather</hi> countenanced in thoſe <hi>falſe reports,</hi> when they bring them, without <hi>a due inquiry,</hi> in order to peace and impartial juſtice, that the <hi>nocent</hi> may be puniſhed, and the <hi>innocent</hi> cleared and ſecured from injury and violence in their habitations, which is no leſs their native right than any others whatſoever, as therefore <hi>ſubjection</hi> is expected from <hi>all,</hi> let <hi>equal protection</hi> be adminiſtred and aſſured likewiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 19</head>
               <p>Now for as much as <hi>among others</hi> bearing the name of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> the name of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> is mainly ſingled out for <hi>publick reproach,</hi> if not for <hi>ruine,</hi> and that their <hi>grand</hi> Impeachment is their oppoſing <hi>Magiſtracy, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</hi> upon which account the <hi>Munſter Tragedy</hi> is ſo <hi>much</hi> and <hi>often</hi> in all places (by Prints, and otherwiſe) laid to <hi>their</hi> charge, as indeed it could not <hi>lightly</hi> be <hi>more,</hi> if thoſe bearing that name in <hi>England</hi> had been the very <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119445:10"/>
actors thereof at <hi>Munſter,</hi> will not the <hi>ſtones ſpeak,</hi> if all <hi>men</hi> ſhould be wholly <hi>mute</hi> under ſuch <hi>clamours?</hi> Wherefore in anſwer hereunto, I hope it will not be a crime very briefly to <hi>apologize</hi> ſo far as to do <hi>them truth,</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> it ſelf a <hi>little right,</hi> without doing <hi>others</hi> any <hi>wrong,</hi> further than to undeceive them, and exonerate <hi>all</hi> as much as may be from <hi>mispriſions,</hi> which in this and other things are the <hi>bane</hi> and <hi>poyſon</hi> of publick peace and amity.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let it be noted that <hi>other ſorts</hi> of men in <hi>England</hi> do impeach one the other with the <hi>ſame crime; ſome</hi> men charge the <hi>whole Parliament</hi> both <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Vindiciae Regum,</hi> or <hi>The grand Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Gr. Williams</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Oſſory.</hi> Alſo Dr. <hi>Fern. Salmaſius. Mr.</hi> Edw: Symons <hi>the Loyal Subjects belief] with the ſeveral An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers unto theſe by other Miniſters.</hi>
                  </note> their <hi>adherents,</hi> with <hi>reſiſting the Authority of the King,</hi> ſaying, Such of them were onely <hi>loyal obedient Subjects</hi> who went to <hi>Oxford</hi> upon the <hi>Kings Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> to ſit in <hi>Parliament</hi> there, or to aid and aſſiſt him in his War. <hi>Others</hi> charge all thoſe <hi>Members</hi> who have <hi>eſpouſed</hi> the <hi>Secluſion</hi> of ſo many of their <hi>own Houſe,</hi> and turned out the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Lords; others</hi> have been adjudged and proceeded againſt as <hi>Delinquents</hi> both formerly and lately for <hi>reſiſting the Parliament</hi> upon the Kings acccount. I modeſtly mention <hi>onely</hi> matters of <hi>fact,</hi> and that but <hi>hints,</hi> without judging the <hi>merit</hi> of them, onely to the end, it may be obſerved, that (ſetting <hi>theſe</hi> aſide) <hi>others</hi> do and will mutually charge with <hi>illegalities</hi> and <hi>exorbitancies</hi> relating to <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil power</hi> and <hi>Government: and indeed things are not judged illegal</hi> (now in our days) <hi>ſo much for what they are ſimply and in themſelves, but either as they may not proſperouſly ſucceed, or as being done by other hands, and not in proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their own intereſt and opinion who ſo judge of them:</hi> which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours more of <hi>faction, paſſion,</hi> and <hi>intereſt,</hi> than of <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> in the eys of <hi>wiſe</hi> obſervers.</p>
               <p>Secondly, their opinion wherein <hi>other Chriſtians</hi> differ from them about the <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>form</hi> of that inſtituted Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is as far <hi>off</hi> the point of <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and oppoſition to it, as <hi>Paedobaptiſm</hi> it ſelf, or any <hi>other</hi> thing in the world. What though therefore ſome holding that opinion either in this or other Nations ſhould be in any wiſe <hi>enormous,</hi> yet their opinion and practice of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> would be no <hi>more</hi> impaired nor untrue than our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s and his Apoſtles Doctrine was by the <hi>treachery</hi> of <hi>Judas,</hi> and the apoſtaſie of <hi>multitudes</hi> in the <hi>primitive times.</hi> And why the denomination of <hi>Anabaptists</hi> (which they diſown) ſhould be faſtened upon them, they are yet to ſeek of ſufficient reaſon, not onely ſeeing they acknowledge <hi>but once baptizing,</hi> but alſo they, laying <hi>no more</hi> weight upon that inſtituted Ordinance than upon that other of like inſtitution, <hi>the Lords Supper,</hi> and then <hi>others</hi> do who hold the <hi>other</hi> way of <hi>baptizing;</hi> yet this <hi>name</hi> is <hi>abuſively</hi> put upon them, as if all their <hi>Religion</hi> lay in <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> whereas in the courſe of their Doctrine touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Principles of Faith, and Piety, and Morality in <hi>Chriſtian</hi> practice, is ſuch as is generally received for orthodox: even by the moſt accounted <hi>ſuch,</hi> who have read confeſſions of their Faith, and heard their common Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the generality of the perſons who hold this opinion have given <hi>ſufficient</hi> proof for divers years, that their principles and practices are as <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119445:10"/>
with humane <hi>ſociety,</hi> peaceable <hi>Cohabitation,</hi> and <hi>due ſubjection</hi> to civil <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> Government as any other in the land; nor only do their manifold <hi>Declarations,</hi> if examined, give ſatisfaction in this point, but withal, neither the <hi>time,</hi> nor <hi>place,</hi> nor <hi>perſons of them</hi> can be mentioned, touching any <hi>inſurrection</hi> they ever made againſt the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> but if any perſons of them had done it, would it be <hi>Juſtice</hi> to impute that to the <hi>whole?</hi> would thoſe of <hi>other ways</hi> be ſo judged? of whom there have been <hi>many,</hi> who have both plotted and actually perpetrated publick inſurrections, which yet was never called <hi>the Munſter tragedy of Paedobaptiſts,</hi> becauſe, though the <hi>ſame</hi> reaſon, yet <hi>Moderation</hi> would not allow it, for <hi>perſonal faults</hi> ought to have only <hi>perſonal imputations,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> deſire to do therein, as they would <hi>others</hi> ſhould <hi>deal</hi> with them.</p>
               <p>As what hath been ſaid will much <hi>obviate</hi> an objection, touching thoſe <hi>few</hi> of <hi>this way</hi> in the <hi>Army:</hi> ſo let me add, that what they have done in that <hi>publick capacity</hi> under an opinion of <hi>publick obligation</hi> hath been ſo far <hi>perſonal,</hi> and as members of the <hi>Nation,</hi> that ſuch do wrongfully who impute it unto their <hi>profeſſion;</hi> but if it muſt needs be ſo, then let it be tryed and proved whether there have not been <hi>[many]</hi> called <hi>Paedobaptiſts,</hi> joynt in all thoſe very actions <hi>for [one] of thoſe,</hi> called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> even in the <hi>higheſt acts</hi> done, whatever unfairly and diſingenuouſly hath been by any repreſented <hi>otherwiſe</hi> to the world. Neither have theſe things been done in <hi>corners,</hi> to be hid from the eyes of <hi>indifferent</hi> ſpectators, who are well able to judge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, As touching <hi>thoſe now,</hi> who hold ſome opinions about Chriſts Kingdom on earth in a reputed offenſive way; is it not notorious, that they are many of them <hi>Paedobaptiſts themſelves,</hi> and as much againſt thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> as others, even as well in the ſubject of baptiſme? and on the <hi>other hand,</hi> the generality of thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> are as much againſt all their offenſive opinions in thoſe points (though ſome few of <hi>one</hi> as well as the <hi>other</hi> ſort may own them) as any others in the world pittying, thoſe who <hi>erre</hi> therein, and <hi>publickly</hi> in their congregations and doctrines detecting ſuch <hi>errors,</hi> diſclaiming and refuting them. Yet albeit, there are many ſuch called <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> of them, the <hi>others</hi> have more of <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>Moderation,</hi> than to lay the <hi>Munſter Tragedy</hi> upon that <hi>name,</hi> though there may be the <hi>ſame</hi> ground. If therefore there ſhould be any <hi>Exorbitant Irruption</hi> in <hi>words</hi> or <hi>actions</hi> of that ſort of people, <hi>thus mixt,</hi> either let ſuch fault be reputed meerly <hi>perſonal,</hi> and no further, or elſe <hi>Indifferently, Juſtly</hi> and <hi>Impartially</hi> be imputed to <hi>one ſort</hi> as well as <hi>another,</hi> more than hitherto it hath been, which indeed (among other things) may <hi>juſtly</hi> call in queſtion the <hi>juſtice</hi> of <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> touching the <hi>Munſter people,</hi> which was about 130 years paſt<hi>:</hi> foraſmuch as <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> is ſo much <hi>wronged</hi> before our <hi>eyes,</hi> and at our own <hi>doors,</hi> as it is by <hi>publick prints</hi> and <hi>otherwiſe</hi> dayly.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, All Hiſtorians about the ſeditions in <hi>Germany</hi> confeſs <hi>thus far inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuoſly,</hi> that the <hi>intolerable oppreſſions</hi> of the Magiſtrates then, gave one <hi>great</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their <hi>riſe</hi> and <hi>progreſs</hi> to that heighth. Wherefore at the ſame time, (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year of our Lord 1525.) in <hi>Suevia</hi> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> there aroſe in arms about forty thouſand men, (who pretended nothing at all to that called Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſme) to exonerate and acquit themſelves by force from their heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119445:11"/>
which was more a rebellion than the other: for they killed the greateſt part of the Nobility, pilledged, ſackt and burnt their houſes, Caſtles and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, and violently overflowed and deſtroyed the Country like an inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet concerning <hi>theſe,</hi> we have <hi>only</hi> the <hi>gentle tender hints</hi> of our <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriographers,</hi> giving us in few lines <hi>meerly narrative of fact,</hi> without any odium on their <hi>fault,</hi> or any <hi>black characters</hi> at all upon their <hi>Names, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> when as the ſame hiſtory of the ſame fact imputed to ſome called Anabaptiſts there, is wrote in moſt dreadful letters of <hi>blood,</hi> concerning their perſons, names and religion, which (by the way) may guide the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial reader in his obſervation and credit of hiſtories wrote by adverſaries. Now ſomewhat contemporary with this great inſurrection (according to the ſame ſtories) <hi>Caroloſtadius, Stock, Muntzer,</hi> and other publick Miniſters of the Goſpel (as <hi>Luther</hi> then was) fell from good principles to dangerous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, dreams, enthuſiaſmes, pretences of extraordinary viſions and revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (all which theſe called Anabaptiſts that I defend, do and ever did as much diſclaime and abhorre as any others in the world, holding firmely to the ſacred Word of God, the holy Scriptures) of whom <hi>Muntzer</hi> chiefly manageth theſe opinions with the oppreſſions unto diſturbous practiſes, to his and others ruine and reproach, about ſix or ſeven years after, which was about the years 1531. 1532. and forward; broke out the like unhappy buſtle at the City of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> by <hi>John Becold Knipperdolling,</hi> and one <hi>Bernard Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> a publick Preacher in that City, and this was accompanied with the like fooliſh mad-vain opinions, being as far <hi>remote</hi> from, and as <hi>forraign</hi> unto <hi>theſe</hi> people in <hi>England,</hi> in their <hi>opinions,</hi> as they were in their <hi>perſons, place</hi> and <hi>time;</hi> who therefore are unduely and unworthily called their <hi>ſpawn,</hi> their <hi>off-ſpring</hi> and <hi>generation,</hi> &amp;c. and what not? Howbeit, let it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved how <hi>Monſtrous,</hi> and <hi>prodigious</hi> this is made, and how much the world is made to <hi>ring</hi> of the noiſe of this <hi>One</hi> diſaſter, that happened in <hi>one</hi> little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of time, and how unchriſtianly and unreaſonably it is now <hi>raked</hi> up and <hi>reckoned</hi> to a company of people, who in ſuch things are as innocent now of the like, as they were of that very fact there, being then unborn. Whereas I have mentioned <hi>like fact</hi> at the <hi>ſame time in others,</hi> and may add the like hints in thoſe hiſtories of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> who about 200 years before aroſe, and violently deſtroyed their Lords, and as violently changed (without blame) both their Governours and Government, not reverting to this day; which if thoſe of <hi>Germany</hi> had ſucceeded as proſperouſly they might have been no more blamed. I might infinitely multiply examples, if I ſhould rake in the duſt and aſhes of other ſorts throughout all ages in Chriſtendom, but what need I go farther then our divers and manifold inſurrections in <hi>England,</hi> againſt all kinds and degrees of authorities, nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her need I mention <hi>by whom</hi> they have been perpetrated, yet all this without the leaſt remembrance or reckoning of <hi>Munſter</hi> unto them, or any of them; ſuch is the power of partiality, and prejudice.</p>
               <p>Moreover I muſt not omit to return the readers <hi>eye</hi> again to <hi>Munſter,</hi> of which <hi>ſame</hi> City we have had certain accompt year by year to this very day for ſome conſiderable time, <hi>that they riſe in armes, reſiſt and oppoſe their lawful Magiſtrate, refuſe obedience to his edicts, and maintain the ſame City againſt him by publick force,</hi> and all without the leaſt <hi>brand</hi> of <hi>infamy on them.</hi> On
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119445:11"/>
the other hand ſuch are very great ſtrangers in the world, who know not that in <hi>Holland</hi> are <hi>ver many,</hi> and have been <hi>very long,</hi> that bear the ſame name of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> that are as <hi>famous</hi> for peaceable living and ſubjection, as any others have been <hi>infamous</hi> for the contrary.</p>
               <p>All which ſtrongly reſults and concludes in this, that there is no <hi>end</hi> not <hi>bounds</hi> of impeaching, if there be not <hi>ſtrickt reſtraint</hi> of publick faults unto their <hi>propper Authours,</hi> acquitting <hi>other opinions</hi> they hold, except <hi>only</hi> ſuch opinions as do naturally and directly tend to ſuch faults. Wherein indeed Mr. <hi>Joſhua Scotton</hi> (though a Paedobaptiſt) deals the moſt ingenuouſly of all other, who in his tranſlate of <hi>Guy du Brez German</hi> ſtory calls it, <hi>the German Enthuſiaſt:</hi> in the Title page, and not the <hi>German</hi> Anabaptiſt, and in the latter end of his Epiſtle to the Reader, hath theſe words<hi>: thoſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which he ſtyleth Anabaptiſts between whom and meer diſſenters in the point of Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſme, being otherwiſe Orthodox and peaceable, the Reader ought alwaies conſcientiouſly to diſtinguiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, Let me a little further inforce this by obſerving<hi>:</hi> that all this <hi>German</hi> ſedition that is now (about 130 years after) put to the accompt of the <hi>innocent</hi> reputed Anabaptiſts in <hi>England,</hi> was in <hi>like</hi> manner <hi>as much</hi> charged upon <hi>innocent Luther</hi> at that very day<hi>:</hi> as the <hi>ſame</hi> Hiſtorians do jointly and generally report, and is confeſſed by Mr. <hi>Samuel Clerk in his lives of the Fathers:</hi> yet had they <hi>as much</hi> reaſon for that, (though none at all) ſeeing the <hi>principal</hi> fomenters of the ſedition had been <hi>publick Preachers</hi> of the Goſpel as <hi>Luther</hi> was, who then and thereupon could but purge himſelf, by publick manifeſto (which is yet extant) as <hi>theſe</hi> in <hi>England</hi> have done, time after time, <hi>not only</hi> by their <hi>confeſſion of faith</hi> oft imprinted, ſhewing their conſtancy, beſides their manifold declarations <hi>more particularly</hi> upon this point in hand, but confirmed by <hi>conſtant practice</hi> in their <hi>peaceable cohabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with their ſeveral neighbourhoods both in City and Country.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Is not this <hi>ſame</hi> imputation toſſed like a <hi>ball,</hi> or rather a <hi>ſtone</hi> between the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in general, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in all their paper conteſts, and <hi>which</hi> and <hi>who</hi> can acquit every <hi>individual</hi> of their party? If therefore any <hi>particular perſons</hi> of this <hi>name</hi> ſhould (among others) prove extravagant, it will no more make this <hi>their glorying void,</hi> then that of <hi>others,</hi> who may rather (for want of Moderation) watch for haltings in theſe more than in <hi>all other</hi> ſorts beſides. Its evident then, that the prevalency of <hi>intereſt</hi> and <hi>faction</hi> above <hi>commutative juſtice, right and reaſon,</hi> in too many of this age doth influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence them to this great unfairneſs, which whether the deſign be (in this way) to <hi>ſtifle</hi> their <hi>opinion</hi> about <hi>baptiſme,</hi> or to bring <hi>ſwift deſtruction</hi> upon thoſe who hold it, though they hold it with never ſo much <hi>piety</hi> towards God, <hi>righteouſneſs and peace</hi> towards men: <hi>Moderation and reſpect</hi> towards thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who conſcientiouſly differ from them, yet (leaving that to God that knows their purpoſes &amp; is above them) they deſire the Lord to forgive thoſe who thus <hi>traduce</hi> them, and <hi>detract</hi> them, and that (through the aſſiſtance of Gods grace) they may be enabled to walk inoffenſively towards Jew or Gentile or Church of God, ſo as to put to ſilence the ignorance of all fooliſh men, who delight to ſpeak evil of <hi>what</hi> and of <hi>whom</hi> they know not, at leaſt many of them.</p>
               <p>Eigthly, As touching extraordinary <hi>Impulſes, Enthuſiaſmes, Dreams, Viſions,</hi> &amp;c. Such who lay all this upon thoſe called Anabaptiſts promiſcuouſly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119445:12"/>
in <hi>England,</hi> they ſhew themſelves to be <hi>very great ſtrangers,</hi> not underſtanding whereof they do affirm, the contrary whereof ſhineth ſo bright, <hi>as</hi> in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary teachings and Church Government; <hi>ſo</hi> in the manifold Treatiſes, Commentaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> printed and publiſhed by many learned of them, upon all points in the Chriſtian Religion. Wherein let it be <hi>duely</hi> noted, that one grand occaſion of this and ſuch like imputations, is plainly this: That one writing Author meeting with <hi>Heterodox</hi> and groſs opinions in his readings of others, laid upon that <hi>name,</hi> he tranſmits it to another that follows, and ſo the <hi>ſecond</hi> to the <hi>third,</hi> and none of all (for the moſt part) receiving any ſuch affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the perſons themſelves, much leſs from any confeſſion of faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the judgment of the <hi>generality</hi> of that name, by which both writers and readers both do and ſuffer wrong in creating to themſelves and others groundleſs prejudices, conveying them over from age to age, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring them a hiddeous monſtrous people<hi>:</hi> and though I could multiply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances hereof in my own ſmall readings, yet I ſhall mention but <hi>one,</hi> which was called a Catalogue of the damnable errors of the Anabaptiſts, enumerating <hi>thirty</hi> and <hi>one;</hi> Yet of <hi>all</hi> theſe, there was but that <hi>one</hi> reputed error of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paedobaptiſme, which they will eſpouſe, diſavowing the reſt as much as he that accuſed them, who was a Miniſter of no inferior note, yet ſhall I forbear to mention any names, becauſe I want not due regard to ſuch perſons, who may be otherwiſe godly and ſerviceable in both teaching and writing, ſetting aſide ſuch miſpriſions, and with all few obſerving readers are unacquainted herewith, to need inſtances.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Neither is it leſs manifeſt, that moſt of thoſe very errors are held and maintained by <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> one againſt the other, the manifold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts among them about moſt <hi>Principal</hi> points of <hi>Doctrine;</hi> and alſo moſt things appertaining to <hi>Church Government</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtration of all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> have been upon the houſe top to be publickly known and read of <hi>all</hi> men, more particularly thoſe called of the <hi>Epiſcopal, Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Eraſtian</hi> ways, not to mention more, nor yet theſe with the leſt immoderate ſpirit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, but <hi>rather</hi> deſiring it may be uſed by them to a moderation of mind towards each other, and alſo to enquire whether the <hi>reputed errors</hi> chargeable upon thoſe called Anabaptiſts, are any way comparable in <hi>number</hi> or <hi>weight</hi> to thoſe in Controverſie among themſelves, and whether the cauſe of ſuch eſtrangedneſs and enmity (on their part) be not miſunderſtanding, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of ſome kind or other, which in like manner hath led themſelves to ſuch <hi>heat</hi> of oppoſition, as hath ended in <hi>removing</hi> and <hi>revolving</hi> of <hi>Church Governments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, To conclude theſe particulars upon this general Section, we find the ſtories of a company of people in <hi>Germany,</hi> who are long ſince dead and buried, under the greateſt reproach and infamy that can be, of whom none can be left to anſwer for themſelves, their reported <hi>Extirpation</hi> and <hi>Extinction</hi> being about 130 years paſt, their riſe and fall, <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>deaths</hi> wrote by their <hi>adverſaries,</hi> no <hi>aggravating</hi> circumſtances, either for <hi>opinion</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> ſeems to be omitted, no <hi>extenuating</hi> paſſages <hi>confeſſedly</hi> inſerted; now that upon the <hi>whole,</hi> there might be ſuch a <hi>people</hi> and ſuch <hi>perſons</hi> bearing that appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who (mixt with others) may be faulty in opinions and practices, is a matter much undoubted, but that every <hi>aggravating paſſage</hi> is true, or that any <hi>one</hi> Hiſtorian (admitting him otherwiſe juſt) was an <hi>ear</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119445:12"/>
                  <hi>witneſs</hi> of all their <hi>opinions,</hi> and an <hi>ocular witneſs</hi> of all their <hi>tragical actions</hi> is reaſonably to be <hi>doubted,</hi> and conſequently their teſtimony in every <hi>puncto</hi> not ſo much to be <hi>regarded;</hi> becauſe falſe reports of contrary minded men touching both ſuch and other perſons and things are ſo <hi>abounding</hi> and <hi>notorious,</hi> in our <hi>own</hi> Nation and Age, like that of <hi>Jer.</hi> 20 10. <hi>Report, ſay they, and we will report: they watched for my halting, &amp;c.</hi> In ſo much that indeed we have little ground of credit to common fame (at leaſt) touching <hi>particulars</hi> of <hi>words</hi> or <hi>acts</hi> ſpoken or done at the very next town, and leaſt of all from <hi>adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> to the perſons and things reported of; yet all ſuch things thus brought upon the <hi>wings</hi> of <hi>fame</hi> is notwithſtanding as commonly and credibly <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> and thereupon again <hi>reported,</hi> yea <hi>printed</hi> and <hi>publiſhed</hi> even in all the aggravating circumſtances, as if nothing in the world were more authentique and indubitable, ſuch is the blinde and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſh <hi>credulity</hi> of men (though ſome otherwiſe honeſt) where they are <hi>prediſpoſed</hi> and <hi>prefixed</hi> in their affections or diſaffections.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe and admit it granted to be <hi>wholly true,</hi> yet obſerve what <hi>proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>nearneſs</hi> of relation is there between <hi>thoſe</hi> perſons and enormities in <hi>Germany</hi> to <hi>theſe</hi> now in <hi>England, that their eating of ſowre grapes ſhould ſet the teeth of theſe on edge?</hi> For there is not any <hi>one</hi> thing of <hi>agreement</hi> is or can be pretended but in that of <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and if the ſtories themſelves be true, they do not <hi>ſo much</hi> agree in that neither, (all things conſidered and obſerved) as thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Poedobaptiſts</hi> do here agree; for they relate, that they grounded their practice of Baptiſm upon pretences of <hi>immediate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> that they baptized <hi>all</hi> who came unto them, that they threatned <hi>damnation</hi> to <hi>all</hi> who neglected it, that they forced <hi>all</hi> perſons to be baptized by proclaiming that all who refuſed <hi>it</hi> ſhould be killed; all which ſignifie ſo much of frenzy and madneſs, that to thoſe of <hi>that name</hi> in <hi>England</hi> nothing is more abſurd and abominable, and that there were ever any ſuch rude and heady perſons, anſwerable to this their portraicture &amp; picture, ſcarce any thing <hi>to them</hi> is more <hi>incredible.</hi> Beſides their practices of <hi>Poligamy,</hi> and deſtroying pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety is unto theſe in <hi>England</hi> deteſtable, and <hi>both</hi> (among other things) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected in their <hi>Declaration</hi> 1647. Wherefore I do humbly and fairly propoſe on their behalf in <hi>England,</hi> that if the <hi>denomination</hi> of <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> be derived <hi>from,</hi> or at leaſt imputed reproachfully <hi>upon</hi> that abominable abuſe of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by theſe men in <hi>Germany,</hi> (waving the proper ſignification of the word as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duly applied) that then and from henceforth theſe who bear the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> may be for ever acquitted and diſcharged thereof, never more to be called by that <hi>name,</hi> which diſcharge is a <hi>due debt</hi> from <hi>juſtice it ſelf,</hi> ſeeing they can as clearly and truly plead <hi>[not guilty]</hi> as any other people in the world; but if any <hi>notwithſtanding all</hi> muſt ſtill needs <hi>reproach</hi> them with this <hi>name of reproach,</hi> that then and therewithall (as of right they ought) they do fully and particularly acquit and diſcharge them from thoſe horrid exorbitancies of opinion and practice <hi>ſaid</hi> to be perpetrated by theſe <hi>German</hi> people, and uſually (hand over head) attributed to <hi>all</hi> that bear this <hi>name,</hi> in <hi>England:</hi> for let but other men ſuppoſe their <hi>own names</hi> and <hi>reputatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in <hi>theſe</hi> mens ſtead, and that they do ſtand <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> from theſe pretended faults, and then nothing would be to them more apparently <hi>equitable</hi> and <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,</hi> than that <hi>all ſuch</hi> ſhould enjoy <hi>the precious ointment of their good</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119445:13"/>
                  <hi>name,</hi> conſidering alſo that it is one <hi>great</hi> Branch of the <hi>ſecond Table of the Law</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>good name</hi> of our Neighbour, as well as life, liberty, eſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> More eſpecially do I urge this, that <hi>Gods name</hi> and <hi>Chriſts name</hi> that is called <hi>upon</hi> theſe people, and called upon <hi>by them,</hi> may not be blaſphemed upon by any miſpriſions or miſtakes, which is (I hope) more dear to them than their own names or humane concerns.</p>
               <p>Moreover, let not any hereafter <hi>travel</hi> beyond the <hi>Seas,</hi> ſo far as <hi>Germany</hi> to <hi>underſtand;</hi> and <hi>calculate</hi> any people in <hi>England,</hi> nor yet look upon <hi>theſe</hi> in <hi>England</hi> through the <hi>bloody Proſpective-glaſs</hi> of <hi>Munſter,</hi> but look upon them with their <hi>own eyes</hi> in their <hi>writings,</hi> and hear them with their <hi>own ears</hi> in their <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and then obſerve the <hi>generality</hi> in their ordinary <hi>converſations,</hi> and either compare them with the <hi>Word</hi> of God, or with <hi>other ſorts</hi> of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or <hi>themſelves,</hi> and do all this without prejudice, partiality, and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, (that being like the diſtemper of the <hi>Yellow Jaundies,</hi> which doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the <hi>object</hi> as <hi>yellow</hi> as the <hi>eye)</hi> but allow <hi>them</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> grains for frailty with <hi>others,</hi> and then make a <hi>Judgement</hi> on them <hi>freely,</hi> and if upon the whole you judge they erre (as who may not) then <hi>without</hi> reproaching, or uſing vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, deal with them in <hi>ſuch a Chriſtian manner</hi> as you will do thoſe of your <hi>own</hi> way, and as you would <hi>others</hi> ſhould do to you<hi>:</hi> this is <hi>Moderation,</hi> which teacheth to conſider that if <hi>they diſſent</hi> from you, <hi>ſo do you</hi> from them, ye are <hi>both in the ſame</hi> predicament</p>
               <p>But if yet further any will think themſelves concerned to write an <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> let me crave leave to make a few <hi>fair in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> Propoſals, to them, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That they will write from <hi>exact</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> knowledge of them, and not upon rumours and reports. 2. That they <hi>charge</hi> nothing upon the <hi>whole</hi> or <hi>generality</hi> of them, but what bears their <hi>own publick</hi> and <hi>general</hi> impreſſion. 3. That where <hi>Paedobaptiſts</hi> are <hi>equally</hi> or <hi>jointly</hi> concerned <hi>with them</hi> in <hi>any</hi> errours or faults, they may not be <hi>partially ſevered;</hi> but <hi>faithfully</hi> and <hi>expreſly</hi> put together; ſetting down <hi>(both alike)</hi> their <hi>denominations</hi> by which they may be <hi>equally</hi> known: to exemplifie this further, that no Errour in Doctrine or manners be <hi>imputed,</hi> at leaſt not <hi>appropriate</hi> unto them, that is not <hi>peculiar</hi> but <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> but if it ſhall be found that any <hi>Proteſtant Paedobaptiſts,</hi> have in <hi>any</hi> place, and at <hi>any</hi> time held or done the <hi>ſame</hi> or <hi>like,</hi> then muſt <hi>that</hi> be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly</hi> mentioned, and <hi>ingenuouſly</hi> confeſſed with it alſo. 4. That no faults be <hi>inſerted</hi> but <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>neceſſarily</hi> follow from <hi>that</hi> opinion that is the <hi>occaſion</hi> of their <hi>diſtinguiſhing denomination.</hi> 5. That ſuch faults may onely be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, as wherein they were <hi>wilfully obſtinate</hi> and <hi>pertinacious</hi> in their preſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and perſiſtance after all <hi>due Chriſtian</hi> means uſed for their conviction and recovery to a rectitude. 6. That the ſtory be reſtrained to the People of that Age and Countrey, and not the faults of others put to their account. 7. That ſuch Errours may be inſiſted upon (if any be) that are <hi>incompatible</hi> with the <hi>temporal ſafety</hi> of the <hi>bodies properties,</hi> and <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>eternal ſafety</hi> of the <hi>ſouls</hi> of men. 8. <hi>Finally,</hi> that all this may be <hi>fairly</hi> done (like the four <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> writing of the Hiſtory of the <hi>Goſpel)</hi> whiles <hi>all things</hi> are freſh in <hi>memory,</hi> and the <hi>perſons concerned</hi> yet <hi>living</hi> and at <hi>liberty</hi> to anſwer for themſelves, leaſt men in the ſtating <hi>others cauſe</hi> and their <hi>own</hi> may <hi>ſeem juſt, and their Neighbour not have oportunity to ſearch them. Prov.</hi> 18. 17. in which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119445:13"/>
caſe it may be ſaid, as <hi>Job</hi> 6. 24, 25. <hi>Teach me and I will hold my tongue, cauſ me to underſtand wherein I have erred,</hi> and <hi>How forcible are right words? but what do your</hi> [ſuch] <hi>arguings</hi> reprove? To which may be added that <hi>remarkable</hi> Dictate of <hi>Nicodemus, Doth our Law judge any man before it hear him and know what he doth? John</hi> 6. 51. Contrariwiſe, the <hi>Backbiter</hi> and his <hi>backbiting</hi> is reckoned and ranked among the worſt of ſins and ſinners, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 30. And, <hi>Who</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) ſhall abide in thy tabernacle? Who ſhall dwell in thine holy hill? Pſalm:</hi> 15. 1. What is the anſwer? <hi>(verſ.</hi> 4.) <hi>He that backbiteth not with his tongue, nor doth evil to his Neighbour, nor taketh up a reproach againſt his Neighbour.</hi> As moſt certainly, <hi>Every man muſt give an account for every [idle word,] Matth.</hi> 12. 36. ſo alſo for every <hi>[hard ſpeech,]</hi> either ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God or good men, <hi>Jude v.</hi> 15. O that all men, <hi>eſpecially Chriſtians</hi> (of all ſides and ſorts) would lay theſe and ſuch like <hi>Scriptures ſeriouſly</hi> to their hearts, and <hi>accordingly</hi> and <hi>conſcientiouſly</hi> ponder the <hi>words</hi> of <hi>their mouths,</hi> and <hi>paths</hi> of their <hi>feet,</hi> which indeed would yield <hi>as much</hi> inward peace and comfort to their <hi>own ſouls,</hi> as <hi>honour</hi> to God, and <hi>credit</hi> to their <hi>Chriſtian</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>That I may be <hi>indifferent</hi> and <hi>impartial</hi> towards <hi>all,</hi> let me in <hi>like</hi> manner on the <hi>other</hi> hand, not ſpare to warn thoſe called <hi>Independents, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, &amp;c.</hi> againſt the ſame evil of <hi>Immoderation,</hi> both in the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of either <hi>words</hi> or <hi>carriages</hi> towards thoſe who are <hi>godly, Miniſters</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> called of the <hi>national way;</hi> in order to which, let me adviſe the reading of that excellent <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of Mr. <hi>William Allen</hi> forerunning his <hi>Book,</hi> entituled <hi>[A Glaſs of Juſtification] And let your Moderation in this respect be known to all men.</hi> It is one <hi>great</hi> proof of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to <hi>value, eſteem,</hi> and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> the image of <hi>Chriſt where ever it is;</hi> which that you may <hi>ſee</hi> more in them or <hi>ſome</hi> of them, be <hi>more Chriſtianly</hi> converſant with and <hi>leſs</hi> eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from them. As you will manifeſt a Goſpel-ſpirit, forbear <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and reprove in others all <hi>harſh, cenſorious,</hi> and <hi>reproachfull</hi> ſpeech, <hi>and all immodeſt</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellations. <hi>Let your ſpeech be always with grace, ſeaſoned with ſalt, that ye may know how ye ought to anſwer every man, Col.</hi> 4. 6. which is <hi>with meekneſs and fear:</hi> 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3 15. <hi>If you would not judge ſo [as] to be judged, Matth.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>Then learn to judge [as] you would be judged. Give</hi> the ſame you will <hi>take, and do to them as you would they ſhould do to you, this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and this is taught by the great Prophet. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 12. And as on the <hi>one hand</hi> you ſhould avoid all ſuch <hi>ſcurrilous</hi> and <hi>provoking</hi> ſpeech, as <hi>altogether unbecoming</hi> the Goſpel, ſo on the <hi>other hand,</hi> withhold not any <hi>due</hi> reſpect, and encouragement you are capable of giving to <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>labour</hi> in the Word and Doctrine, though they may not be in all reſpects of your <hi>opinion</hi> and <hi>way,</hi> remembring that <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Diſciples, being cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iouſly offended with <hi>thoſe that followed not with them,</hi> and therefore provoked him to <hi>forbid</hi> them do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>good work,</hi> they were in ſtead thereof <hi>rebuked</hi> for their labour, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 49, 50. which is a teaching Example unto us, <hi>as</hi> not to <hi>hinder,</hi> ſo to <hi>further any</hi> ſervice for <hi>God,</hi> eſpecially that in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> tending to the eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>ſouls</hi> of men. Is it not <hi>very</hi> ſad to think <hi>how many thouſands</hi> of poor ſouls <hi>may periſh for want of knowledge,</hi> if the ſupply of <hi>all</hi> places depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>onely</hi> on the preaching of ſome <hi>one way.</hi> Let thoſe then of <hi>every way</hi> be countenanced and encouraged, <hi>who</hi> by <hi>ſound</hi> Doctrine, and dividing the <hi>Word</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119445:14"/>
                  <hi>aright,</hi> may give to <hi>every one</hi> their portion in <hi>due ſeaſon,</hi> that if it be the will of God, the <hi>weighty</hi> work of <hi>Converſion</hi> (I mean from the power of Satan unto God) may be <hi>more</hi> revived and made proſperous throughout all the dark corners of the land: that all our <hi>ſtrenuous ſtrifes</hi> may be reſolved into this, who ſhall <hi>moſt excel</hi> in vertue, and gather in <hi>moſt</hi> wheat of Gods harveſt <hi>out</hi> of the field, <hi>into</hi> his Garner.</p>
               <p>And for my ſelf, wherein <hi>to ſome degree,</hi> I have been in former time, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with this <hi>common</hi> infirmity of harſhneſs in judging others: I do hereby publickly retract it, having better learned to hold <hi>thoſe</hi> opinions <hi>modeſtly,</hi> about <hi>leſſer</hi> matters, wherein <hi>ſo many</hi> able and godly men may be of another mind. And therefore in that particular (without inconſtancy) to redeem my time in <hi>Moderating,</hi> as far as my <hi>ſmall</hi> talent, and a <hi>pure</hi> conſcience to God and men will carry me. Wherein I have for ſome <hi>later</hi> years diſpoſed my ſelf, not upon any <hi>ſiniſter</hi> conſiderations, (which is known to the Lord) but from <hi>Judgement, Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> which whatever ſucceſs it hath had on <hi>others,</hi> yet not without reflection of comfort to my <hi>ſelf:</hi> all which I direct to thoſe <hi>aforementioned,</hi> if it may be to reaſon them into (no other then) a <hi>Chriſtian Moderation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the rather whereas ſome <hi>few</hi> of that <hi>name</hi> aforeſaid, (far from conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the generality) being yet <hi>ſowre</hi> and <hi>harſh</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>called</hi> of the <hi>national way,</hi> have caſt upon them the <hi>names</hi> of <hi>Antichristian</hi> and <hi>Babyloniſh,</hi> whom though I <hi>tender</hi> for that they may be <hi>otherwiſe</hi> godly, yet let me ſay without <hi>partiality,</hi> that this doth not proceed from the wiſdom that's from above, that's <hi>gentle</hi> and <hi>peaceable,</hi> as well as <hi>pure,</hi> Jam. 3. 17. and its different from the Tenour of that <hi>Declaration dated and publiſhed,</hi> Decemb. 12. 1659. in the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>many</hi> called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> which however its harſhly, weakly and miſtakingly interpreted; yet is it well known (to many wiſe obſervers) that the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>ſober ſpirit</hi> thereof, is no <hi>new thing,</hi> but contrariwiſe a conſtant purſuance of the <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>humble ſpirit</hi> of the old <hi>confeſſion</hi> of their <hi>faith,</hi> and many other <hi>old</hi> Declarations, to which they <hi>firmly</hi> adhere, ſome particulars of <hi>whom</hi> ſhould have been here recited, had it not been for avoyding <hi>prolixity</hi> and <hi>tediouſneſs</hi> to the reader<hi>:</hi> ſave only this muſt be duely obſerved, that <hi>even</hi> thoſe perſons firſt above mentioned, do alſo acquit and diſcharge themſelves from <hi>thoſe</hi> aſperſions about <hi>ſubjection</hi> to Magiſtracy and <hi>peaceable</hi> cohabitation among other men, though ſomewhat ſevere againſt thoſe of the national way, and the more becauſe they judge them of a perſecuting ſpirit.</p>
               <p>But with ſuch who <hi>thus</hi> exert the harſhneſs of their ſpirits in a girding cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring ſpeech, let me in few words expoſtulate: you account thoſe of the <hi>national way Babyloniſh, Antichriſtian,</hi> theſe are very <hi>big</hi> and <hi>ambiguous</hi> [words,] <hi>eaſily</hi> ſpoken, more <hi>hardly</hi> underſtood, yet <hi>too</hi> commonly toſſed to and fro upon diſagreement in the <hi>ſmalleſt puncto's</hi> of opinion, by thoſe who never explain <hi>thoſe words and things,</hi> to demonſtrate from the Word of God, <hi>where</hi> and <hi>who</hi> deſerves the Imputations. But whereas you <hi>Impute</hi> thoſe names, may not they <hi>retort</hi> them back on you with other additions, and you again on <hi>others,</hi> and <hi>ſo</hi> run the <hi>circle?</hi> for where will this <hi>end,</hi> and to what doth it <hi>tend,</hi> but to make many judge you <hi>all</hi> in <hi>Babylon?</hi> &amp;c. and ſo run either to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or to Atheiſme and prophaneneſs. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith) <hi>What do ſuch arguings reprove?</hi> who will be ever the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119445:14"/>
                  <hi>better</hi> or the <hi>wiſer?</hi> who is hereby convinced of an <hi>error,</hi> or brought to the <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of any <hi>one</hi> truth? nay rather doth it not <hi>prejudice</hi> others againſt you and your differing opinions? The like may be ſaid on the other hand of thoſe who uſe the words <hi>Sectary, Fanatick,</hi> &amp;c. upon every trivial difference, as if that were enough to confute an opinion, or make it ever the worſe. But would it not be a <hi>good</hi> expedient, and better becoming wiſe men and ſober Chriſtians on <hi>all</hi> hands, inſtead of giving foul and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>names</hi> to a <hi>reputed</hi> error in <hi>others,</hi> to aſſert rather <hi>poſitively</hi> and <hi>modefily</hi> what themſelves do hold for <hi>truth,</hi> and then uſe the moſt <hi>pregnant</hi> arguments to convince thereof, and the moſt <hi>powerful</hi> Motives to perſwade thereto. In which <hi>way,</hi> men may kill <hi>three</hi> birds with <hi>one</hi> ſtone <hi>(viz.) convince</hi> of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>informe</hi> in the truth, and manifeſt to others, you hold your opinions for <hi>conſcience</hi> and not <hi>contention:</hi> and if you muſt needs give error a <hi>name,</hi> then call it <hi>error,</hi> and <hi>well</hi> confute it, and deal not <hi>oprobriouſly</hi> with any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who may hold it, which never will <hi>convince them,</hi> but <hi>reflect</hi> the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of malice and envy upon your <hi>ſelves,</hi> and ſtir it up in <hi>others,</hi> whereby <hi>too</hi> commonly the <hi>truth it ſelf</hi> between <hi>both,</hi> is drowned and loſt in jars and diſcords, and perſons gradually loſe their ſpiritual <hi>ſavour,</hi> and grow ſtrangers to <hi>godly</hi> edifying<hi>:</hi> by all which faults on both hands, this follows, that <hi>Ichabod</hi> is ſadly written upon <hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>glory thereof being much departed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 21.</head>
               <p>And becauſe the fault of this kind is of both ſides, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore offer to both. I hope its well underſtood on both ſides, that the <hi>main</hi> of Religion and <hi>power</hi> of godlineſs, doth neither <hi>only</hi> nor <hi>chiefly,</hi> but <hi>leaſt</hi> of all lye in thoſe particular <hi>inſtituted</hi> matters, which are the matters in <hi>difference:</hi> why then the conteſt ſhould be <hi>ſo hot</hi> and <hi>ſevere,</hi> accompanied with <hi>ſo great</hi> alienations and oppoſitions on <hi>both</hi> ſides, for my part I underſtand not, <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> when I conſider that the difference is not ſo much about the <hi>Doctrinal</hi> part, as the manner of <hi>practiſing</hi> thoſe particular inſtitutions. But the <hi>plain main</hi> things of Chriſtianity then are ſummarily ſuch as theſe, wherein thoſe called <hi>Puritans</hi> of old did excel, <hi>viz.</hi> right principles of doctrine about <hi>God</hi> the Father, Son, and holy Spirit; the right way of <hi>Juſtification</hi> by Gods grace through a <hi>lively</hi> ſaith in the <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, in oppoſition to the <hi>merit</hi> of inherent righteouſneſs, or external works. This <hi>rectitude</hi> in the point of <hi>juſtification,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> calls it, and Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſs</hi> likewiſe well, <hi>its both the ſoul and pillar of Chriſtianity:</hi> Together with the great work of <hi>regeneration</hi> by the holy Spirit, cooperating with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, likewiſe <hi>progreſſive ſanctification,</hi> chiefly conſiſting in a conſtant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued courſe of <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith, Mortification of ſin</hi> and luſt, <hi>lively exerciſe</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> in all good and holy works, <hi>(viz.)</hi> whether Practice of Piety in all Chriſtian duties, <hi>moral</hi> or <hi>inſtituted,</hi> either <hi>publick</hi> or <hi>private,</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately towards God: Or <hi>righteouſneſs, love</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> towards men, either in <hi>propper</hi> and <hi>peculiar</hi> relations, or in <hi>common</hi> towards our neighbour and <hi>all</hi> men <hi>even</hi> our enemies; finally <hi>perſeverance</hi> in all this to the ſecond coming of Chriſt to raiſe the bodies of the dead, and render to every man according to his works, with eternal happineſs in heaven, or eternal miſery in hell. Foraſmuch then, as there is an agreement very much <hi>mutually</hi> known about all theſe and much more (except only that one branch of inſtitutions) is there not a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand fold more reaſon of <hi>Moderation</hi> and mutual <hi>tenderneſs</hi> and <hi>forbearance,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119445:15"/>
then of <hi>eſtrangedneſs</hi> and <hi>cenſurings,</hi> and that of one anothers conſciences, even unto a kind of violence upon each others <hi>names, reputations,</hi> &amp;c. neither would I be miſtaken: I urge not the abating of one <hi>hairs breadth</hi> of either <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>form</hi> of an inſtituted ordinance; neither dare I do it, when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>that</hi> the great fall of our firſt Parents (and we in them) was by the breach of an inſtitution, <hi>that</hi> they have Gods ſtamp upon them, <hi>that</hi> he hath been always regardful about the <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> pins and eylet holes, <hi>that</hi> his ſervants in Scripture were careful about them, <hi>that</hi> they have an excellency in their nature, uſe and ends, <hi>that</hi> the Laws of God <hi>Natural, Moral</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> yea and the nature of grace do all comprehend inſtitutions, in a general obedience to the will of God<hi>:</hi> from all which I conclude none of them are to be deſpiſed, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued, neglected, rejected, (as by too many now, highly elevated, they are) nor yet violated by an <hi>undue</hi> adminiſtration of them. But about this laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the manner of adminiſtration is the only queſtion<hi>:</hi> this is like the <hi>Gordian knot,</hi> cut it we muſt not, untye it we cannot, at leaſt not for <hi>another,</hi> though we may each for <hi>himſelf.</hi> Being thus brought to the only general point in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie<hi>:</hi> the next queſtion is, whether its either <hi>unlawful</hi> (for truely moſt do carry it as if it were a vice, and not a vertue) or <hi>impoſſible</hi> for each cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to love one the other, and mutually forbear, and Chriſtianly correſpond? albeit neither be brought to <hi>own</hi> the others opinion. In anſwer to which, ſurely mutual love cannot be either unlawful or impoſſible among true Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, (as all are who believe in Chriſt, and endeavour a purity of conſcience) ſeeing it is the grand duty of all ſuch, above other, and character of ſuch, <hi>John</hi> 13. 35. as alſo agreeable to the whole tenour of the Goſpel, and judged very eaſily practicable by that excellent reconciler <hi>Jacobus Acontius, in his diſcovery of Stratagems of the Devil,</hi> and for my <hi>own</hi> part, I do judge there is no other general impediments than thoſe <hi>Stratagems</hi> of the Devil, and the remaining <hi>corruptions</hi> in the hearts of good men, (which makes me wonder at the folly of thoſe who boaſt of preſent perfection,) neither do I doubt, but that all who can lay aſide <hi>prejudice, paſſion</hi> and private <hi>intereſt,</hi> will judge it both <hi>deſireable</hi> and without <hi>difficulty</hi> for his own part; nor do I know how (in this world) its poſſible ever to come to an <hi>unity</hi> of mind in one <hi>common opinion</hi> of the truth, without firſt a correſpondency in <hi>unity</hi> of <hi>common Chriſtian affection;</hi> nor are the differences much more than the tithing of <hi>Mint, Annis and Cummin,</hi> in compariſon with the <hi>weightier matters both of Law and Goſpel,</hi> which will well and ſafely admit of modeſty and humbleneſs of mind on all ſides, without any hurt to the conſcience. Upon the whole, where lyes then the <hi>Stiffeneſs</hi> and the <hi>ſtick?</hi> who muſt begin firſt to love, and to expreſs it? muſt not every one begin firſt? and will not the <hi>foremen</hi> carry the <hi>greateſt</hi> honour in the ſight of God and Chriſtians? and what hurt or hazard can there be to the <hi>truth</hi> (be it where it will) thus to lay aſide <hi>animoſities, prejudices,</hi> evil <hi>ſurmiſes,</hi> evil <hi>ſpeakings,</hi> and converſe together in an amicable way, without looking upon each other as <hi>Monſters</hi> and <hi>prodigies,</hi> as <hi>too too</hi> much formerly, making every trivial a <hi>bear</hi> and a <hi>lyon</hi> in the way to hinder the <hi>means</hi> of a right underſtanding and aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction</p>
               <p>But if it be <hi>impoſſible</hi> (contrariwiſe) thus to walk in mutual love and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, improving each others gifts and graces as far as may be, unleſs and untill <hi>both</hi> be reſolved into <hi>one</hi> common opinion about every <hi>puncto</hi> of Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119445:15"/>
then muſt it be by an actual complyance on the one hand or the other. If ſo, then this queſtion follows, which of the parties muſt be the <hi>Standard, which</hi> and <hi>who</hi> will ſo arrogate and appropriate to themſelves the <hi>[Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim]</hi> as to whom all <hi>others</hi> muſt in every thing <hi>conform?</hi> again this conforming on the <hi>one</hi> ſide or the <hi>other,</hi> it muſt be <hi>either voluntary</hi> from change of mind, or <hi>conſtrained</hi> by force: the former is not probable to be, becauſe the <hi>way</hi> unto it ſeems to be barr'd, fenc't, hedg'd up by an excluſion of all Chriſtian forbearance and amicable converſe. And for the latter, <hi>viz. Coercion,</hi> that ought not to be, becauſe <hi>both</hi> will and may plead an <hi>equal right</hi> of liberty in the Nation, from being impoſed upon by his neighbour, and <hi>like equal right</hi> of liberty, to judge which is the <hi>exacteſt</hi> way of ſerving God, and the <hi>righteſt</hi> and <hi>directeſt</hi> way to heaven; wherefore the final iſſue whereto ſuch a violent conteſt tends, it is to make our Land an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a <hi>field of blood;</hi> yea (which is worſt of all) of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> blood, which as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God from heaven may <hi>forbid,</hi> as he ſeaſonably ſtaid the hand of <hi>Abraham</hi> over his ſon <hi>Iſaac:</hi> and countermanded the <hi>Angels</hi> drawn deſtroying ſword over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at the threſhing floor of <hi>Araunah</hi> the Jebuſite, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 16. So do I humbly propoſe, that <hi>reaſon, grace,</hi> and the <hi>Royal</hi> law of love and charity may prevail upon the minds of <hi>both,</hi> to meet <hi>each</hi> other in <hi>Moderation,</hi> as the <hi>firſt</hi> ſtep to Chriſtian unity<hi>:</hi> for <hi>you can never be ſwift to hear each other, unleſs you are ſlow to wrath,</hi> Jam. 1. 19. but if after all, any ſhall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> their <hi>wrath,</hi> and <hi>remain</hi> irreconcilable: let ſuch know, <hi>that God knows how to reſtrain it,</hi> Pſal. 76. 10. But were your affections <hi>thus</hi> united, jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and evil ſurmiſes <hi>thus</hi> removed, it would not a little obviate the clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine deſigns of Jeſuits among us, whoſe prevailing argument, drawn from the pretended <hi>unity</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> to prove it <hi>the only true Church,</hi> is ſadly ſtrengthned by our diviſions<hi>:</hi> the danger of which ſort of perſons, is lately ſeaſonably ſuggeſted by the Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> in their printed exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and what gives them ſo great advantage, but the paſſionate bickerings among godly Proteſtants?</p>
               <p>Moreover it would as much prevent a ſtrenuous hurtful conteſt about the Soveraign power between both, which (without a <hi>mutual</hi> ſecurity of this kind, from each others unrightful impoſing) ſeems hard to fix in any hands, but is perpetually rolling to and fro, and ſubjects the nation to continual changes and rotations. And none will then be <hi>blamed,</hi> if they take <hi>all</hi> opportunities and advantages, to relieve and ſecure themſelves from the ſtroke and yoke of others, and ſo others again from them; and what and where will be the end thereof? though the <hi>leaſt juſt blame</hi> will fall on them, who in ſeeking <hi>ſimply</hi> for ſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, ſhall be led to impoſe in any wiſe on <hi>others,</hi> and would not otherwiſe do it, could they but be ſafe in peace and <hi>equal</hi> liberty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 22.</head>
               <p>For as much as thoſe honourable perſons, who ſit in ſupreme Council are Repreſentatives of different ſorts in <hi>common,</hi> and not of any <hi>one</hi> particularly, I do humbly make it my concluding Propoſal, whether ſome thing extraordinary of an indifferent nature, ballancing and ſecuring all ſorts, till by moderation they can arrive at a better underſtanding, and mutual accord, will not moſt naturally tend to our long deſired ſettlement, and beſt become and truly make it a <hi>Common-wealth?</hi> Whether the common peace being kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> ſaved from the <hi>harm</hi> and <hi>hurt</hi> of others, upon <hi>all</hi> accounts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119445:16"/>
                  <hi>whatſoever</hi> be not the principal <hi>end</hi> of Gods ordaining <hi>Government</hi> among the ſons of men, and the <hi>beſt</hi> way to <hi>faſten</hi> and <hi>binde</hi> together all the <hi>integral</hi> parts of this <hi>broken</hi> Nation, put a <hi>period</hi> to all our publick <hi>changes,</hi> and the <hi>way</hi> to prevent all future <hi>fears,</hi> and ſurceaſe all juſt complainings in our ſtreets: <hi>all ſorts</hi> feeling the benefits hereof, willingly aſcribing to ſuch Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours the honour of our Settlement.</p>
               <p>It is humbly hoped, that no <hi>individual perſon</hi> (be he of what religious <hi>Sect</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,) much leſs the <hi>generality</hi> of a <hi>Sect</hi> may be judged, cruſht and laid under reproach upon any harſh counſel and ſuggeſtion of Adverſaries, <hi>without</hi> a full and fair hearing of defence, which is <hi>moſt</hi> expected under a Government of the People, where <hi>no mans caſe</hi> may be ſuppoſed to depend on any <hi>one mans paſſions,</hi> or <hi>intereſt.</hi> This is the more neceſſary and conſiderable, becauſe <hi>whisperers</hi> are always ready to inſinuate what may <hi>ſeparate chief frends, Prov.</hi> 16. 28. There is never wanting ſome who worſhip the <hi>riſing Sun,</hi> and having mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of <hi>advantage,</hi> who neither out of conſcience to God, nor love to Governours, (but like <hi>Doeg</hi> to <hi>David)</hi> to get ſome <hi>benefit</hi> to themſelves, will be laying <hi>loads</hi> upon others, by informations.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it is <hi>deſirable</hi> that <hi>Rulers</hi> may always remember, the beloved Kingdom of God was broken in pieces by <hi>Reheboam</hi>'s taking <hi>harſh</hi> counſel, and refuſing that which was more <hi>moderate,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 6, 10. whereas <hi>David</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>ſuch</hi> counſel in that <hi>petty</hi> perſonal caſe of <hi>curſing Shimei,</hi> when yet he had <hi>full</hi> oportunity to deſtroy him under the <hi>publick</hi> reputation of <hi>juſtice. Such</hi> counſel may ſometimes be given with the intent of hurt and damage to <hi>them</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> it is given, like <hi>Huſhai</hi>'s unto <hi>Abſalom,</hi> or with the <hi>ſame</hi> Deſign the <hi>Phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtims</hi> had upon <hi>Sampſon,</hi> to cut off the locks of his <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore in the midſt of all abilities of counſel, foreſight and force, I humbly propoſe that you will make the <hi>Word</hi> of God the man of your counſel, and that you follow the Example of <hi>Solomon,</hi> to ask of God wiſdom for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not onely becauſe you have a <hi>mighty</hi> People as he had, but a People ſo <hi>greatly</hi> divided, which he had not. As an opinion of ſelf-ſufficiency is a moſt dangerous thing, ſo the <hi>way</hi> to proſper is to depend on God, and the <hi>way</hi> to depend and lean upon God <hi>aright,</hi> is to make ſure of being in the <hi>way</hi> of righteouſneſs and uprightneſs. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee? to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God, Micah</hi> 6. 8. <hi>Remembring how God anſwered from</hi> Shittim <hi>to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>v.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Albeit, I know that the <hi>hearts</hi> of Rulers as well as others are in the <hi>hands</hi> of the Lord, <hi>who can turn them as the Rivers of Waters:</hi> and alſo that God governs and over-rules <hi>all</hi> counſels and affairs by his moſt wiſe and holy provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to his <hi>own</hi> glory, yet doth not <hi>that</hi> diſſolve the bond of duty lying upon <hi>all</hi> to do what ſervice they can for God in their Generation, upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I have adventured to make this humble addreſs to Rulers and all men, if at leaſt it may move them more to a ſtudy of Moderation, then I little doubt the <hi>practice,</hi> and where it may to any degree prevent any <hi>harſh intentions,</hi> ſuch may have no cauſe of repentance, <hi>but</hi> rejoycing like <hi>David,</hi> when he was <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted</hi> by <hi>Abigait</hi>'s <hi>moderation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although I have been, and am <hi>altogether</hi> unconcerned in theſe <hi>mutations</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119445:16"/>
and tranſactions themſelves, yet I muſt be a ſharer (among others) in the good or ill effects and iſſues of them, which gives me ſomewhat of <hi>right</hi> to offer my poor opinion. This I have done with a <hi>ſincere</hi> aim at <hi>common</hi> good, with much <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and ſenſe of mine <hi>own</hi> weakneſs.</p>
               <p>My humble Requeſts to God ſhall be, that he would make ſome (thoſe at the <hi>Stern,</hi> if he pleaſe) to be <hi>Healers</hi> of our <hi>Breaches,</hi> and <hi>Reſtorers</hi> of <hi>Paths</hi> for us to dwell in, that we may live under a well-ſettled <hi>Authority</hi> a quiet and peaceable life in all <hi>godlineſs</hi> and <hi>honeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I hope that in prudence and juſtice, all publick Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and Writers will hereafter forbear that double wrong to their peaceable Subjects and Neighbours; firſt, in giving them unduly the name of <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> and ſecondly, in laying the dirt and dung of a mad miſ-guided People in <hi>one</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Age and forreign Nation upon them, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Germany;</hi> for as much as it will give them occaſion and provocation to retort that greater inſurrection, and thoſe worſer devaſtations of fourty thouſand at the ſame time in <hi>Suevia</hi> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> before recited out of the ſame Hiſtories; as alſo to obſerve all the over-turnings in all Ages and Nations throughout <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> by whom they have been made and perpetrated; all which gendreth and nouriſheth need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſtrife and contention on both hands. Wherefore, contrariwiſe, <hi>Let</hi> all ſorts <hi>follow the things that make for peace, and ſuch things wherewith one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be edified, Rom.</hi> 14. 19.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
